<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Adam Abel, or, Vain man a discourse fitted for funeral occasions, but serviceable to men in all ages and conditions of life to make them humble and heavenly-minded / by Samuel Shaw ...</title>
            <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9572</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13282270</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13282270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98767</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98767)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 439:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Adam Abel, or, Vain man a discourse fitted for funeral occasions, but serviceable to men in all ages and conditions of life to make them humble and heavenly-minded / by Samuel Shaw ...</title>
                  <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 123, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. 123.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pride and vanity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98767:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98767:1"/>
            <p>ADAM ABEL: OR, <hi>Vain Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Fitted for Funeral Occaſions, BUT Serviceable to Men in all Ages and Conditions of Life, to make them humble and Heavenly-minded.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL SHAW,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. XXXIX. 5.</bibl> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and 3 Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98767:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98767:2"/>
            <head>Reverendo in Chriſto Patri, THOMAE TENNISONO, D. Epiſcopo Lincolnienſi. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <p>ERuditionem multifariam, &amp; virtutes, quae D. Opt. Max. Gr. in te plurimae ſunt (ornatiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae praeſes) celebrare vel celibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ire, eſſet <hi>culpâ deterere inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi> Gratias agimus Deo miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, &amp; vicegerenti ejus ſereniſſimo Guilielmo, qui te tui<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſimiles Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae noſtrae praefecerint. Diu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſis &amp; praeſis populo Anglicano <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; ſerus in coelum redeas. Viſum ſit humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati &amp; benignitati tuae, lucubratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus hiſce qualibuſcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> patroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari: Quae licet non olent lucer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, coelum tamen &amp; immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſpirant, &amp; genium licet non
<pb facs="tcp:98767:3"/> ingenium ſapiunt. <hi>Dulce &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum eſt pro patria mori:</hi> At multò certè dulcius &amp; decentius, moriendo ad patriam remigrare. Oh quam juvat videre animam (origine planè divinâ) in carcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam pulvere, vanitatem ſuam agno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentem, mundanas ſordes excutien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, patriae ſuae coeleſti <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antem, &amp; in intimos &amp; artiſſimos centri ſui amplexus trepidantem. Habeat Eccleſia Romana ſuos Quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtas: Sed habeat Eccleſia refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata animas planè inquietas, donec revertantur in ſinum patris coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis! Cujus amori ſuaviſſimo, &amp; omnipotenti gratiae, quam humilimè commendat reverentiam tuam</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Cultorum tuorum ſummus licet infimus, S. SHAW.</signed>
               <dateline>Aſhby de la Zouch, <date>
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 1691/2.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98767:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Adam Abel,</hi> OR, VAIN MAN, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. xxxix. 6.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Profecto vir ambulat in imagine. <hi>Surely every man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Do not know of any one Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, that in all Ages has more ſollicited and perplex'd the Minds of Good men, than that which ſprings from the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Wicked; a Scandal that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98767:4"/> the beſt of Men have been ever apt to take againſt the Diſpenſations of God himſelf; <hi>Quod malis bene fit, &amp; bonis bene;</hi> it hath therefore pleaſed God, in compaſſion to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to obviate this Temptation, by cauſing many parts of holy Scriptures to be written purpoſely upon this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, amongſt which this 39th Pſalm is one, the main Propoſition of which is, an Exhortation, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Proſperity of the Wicked, do not doubt of the Divine Care and Providence: Be not broken in our Minds, do not murmure againſt God, nor fall away from him, but patiently endure Adverſity, and hold faſt our Profeſſion. I ſhall not ſpend time to analize the Pſalm, and ſhew the metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical and artificial Compoſure, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly fall upon the Illuſtration, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and Application of the Words.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Profectò, ſurely</hi> or <hi>verily;</hi> an Adverb of Aſſeveration. But what, is not every Word of God ſure and true,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98767:4"/> and equally true? What then needs any Note of Aſſeveration to one more than another? Though every Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Scripture be equally true, yet ſome Sentences are harder to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd and believ'd than others; <hi>Durus hic ſermo,</hi> ſaid the Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 60. concerning the Doctrine of ſpiritual Manducation; and ſome are of greater weight and importance than others. In theſe two Caſes eſpecially the Adverb of Aſſeveration is wont to be prefix'd, as may appear by many Texts, both in the Old Teſtament and the New; you have an Example of the firſt Caſe in <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 34. <hi>Peter</hi> was confident of his own faithfulneſs and ſtedfaſtneſs, and would not believe any thing to the contrary; <hi>Though all men ſhould be offended becauſe of thee, yet will I never be offended:</hi> To whom our Saviour anſwers with this Aſſeveration, <hi>Verily I ſay unto thee, that this night, before the cock crow, thou ſhalt deny me thrice.</hi> Of the latter Caſe there are abundance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98767:5"/> of Examples; in the Old Teſtament, take that famous Text, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58. 11. <hi>Verily there is a reward for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; verily he is a God that judgeth in the Earth.</hi> And in the new take that as famous, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 3. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> This moſt important Doctrin is twice again uſher'd in with the ſame aſſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 3, 5. <hi>Verily, verily, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a man be born again, &amp;c.</hi> And upon both theſe accounts it is well uſed here, for there is no Doctrine that vain Man is ſlower to believe, nor more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be believ'd; than the Doctrine of his own Vanity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Man] i. e. every man.</hi> By a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Idiom <hi>Man</hi> is put to ſignifie <hi>any man,</hi> or <hi>every man.</hi> Thus both the words, <hi>Iſh</hi> and <hi>Adam,</hi> are uſed. So that <hi>Man</hi> here is no leſs than <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> or, as it is rightly tranſlated in the Text, <hi>Every man.</hi> So <hi>Job</hi> 14. 1.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98767:5"/> 
               <hi>Man that is born of a Woman is of few days, and full of trouble.</hi> The Greeks imitate the Hebrew Idiom in this, as in many other things. <hi>What is a man profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted if he ſhould gain the whole world and loſe his own Soul? Mat.</hi> 16. 26. And again, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. 36. <hi>What ſhall it profit a man, &amp;c?</hi> In ſhort, it cannot be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expreſt in Engliſh, than by <hi>every man,</hi> or by <hi>Mankind,</hi> which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends Women as well as Men. Surely all Mankind <hi>walketh in a vain ſhew, Betſelem, in imagine,</hi> in a ſhew or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. This word is put in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>ſubſtantialneſs</hi> or to <hi>duration;</hi> in both ſences, <hi>man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi> He ſeems to be ſomething when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he is nothing. We talk much of Apparitions of the Dead; certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every living man is but an Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition, he comes upon the Stage of the World, and acts one part or other, but he is not that which he ſeems to be: And as to his <hi>duration,</hi> he is a ſhew or a ſhadow too, ſoon paſſing away
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98767:6"/> 
               <hi>Apparentia ſubito evaneſcens,</hi> ſays the learned <hi>Ravanellus, He fleeth as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and continueth not.</hi> That Text of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 31. comprohends both theſe ſences, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Faſhion</hi> or Scheme <hi>of this World paſſeth away.</hi> It is but a Scheme, a Draught, a Reſemblance of ſomething, and that ſoon paſſes away too: So that there is neither <hi>reality</hi> nor <hi>durability</hi> in Mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Walketh].</hi> This in the Hebrew Idiom ſignifies <hi>lives</hi> or <hi>converſes,</hi> and the word here is of a conjugation that makes it ſignifie very briskly; it is <hi>verbum,</hi> not only <hi>efficax,</hi> but <hi>frequenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivum,</hi> and is as much as to be buſie, and make a great buſtle, even as when <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi> look'd down upon Men converſing upon Earth, and ſaw them buying, ſelling, working, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, trading, fighting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thought they reſembled a company of Piſmires running to and fro about a Hillock: So indeed it is, Man buſtles, and makes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98767:6"/> a mighty ſtir about juſt nothing, and wearies himſelf in very Vanity.</p>
            <p>This word <hi>Walking</hi> comprehends the whole Way and Work of Man, and may be reduc'd, for method ſake, to three Heads, to what he <hi>is,</hi> to what he <hi>has,</hi> to what he <hi>does.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are a great many men in the World, concerning whom every one that ſees them may ſay, They walk in a vain ſhew. <hi>The fool,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 3. <hi>when he walketh by the way, his wiſdom fails him, and he ſaith to every one that he is a fool:</hi> So I may ſay of theſe men, they proclaim their own Vanity. There are thoſe, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> that make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves rich, and yet have nothing, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 7. There are a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny confident Pretenders to Piety, Learning, and other Accompliſhments, who indeed are but a ſounding Braſs, or a tinkling Cymbal, as the Apoſtle phraſes it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1. There are many bold Huffs, that look big, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98767:7"/> talk loud, and run down the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſter ſort of Mortals, when indeed <hi>vox ſunt praetereaque nihil;</hi> or, in the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi>'s Phraſe, <hi>Wells without Water:</hi> But I ſpeak not of theſe, who do loudly proclaim their own Folly and Vanity, to make it notorious to all men; but I am ſpeaking of the Condition of Mankind in general; ſurely every man walketh in <hi>a vain ſhew,</hi> or, as it is in the Verſe going before my Text, <hi>Verily, every man at his beſt eſtate is altogether Vanity.</hi> Every word has an emphaſis with it: In the Hebrew it is very elegant, <hi>Col hebel col Adam, omnimoda vanitas eſt omnis homo. Adam</hi> called his Son <hi>Abel,</hi> but <hi>David</hi> here calls every. <hi>Adam</hi> an <hi>Abel,</hi> elſewhere he ſpeaks more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, That ſo neither great nor ſmall may excuſe themſelves, <hi>Surely men of low degree are Vanity, and men of high degree are a Lye; to be laid in the balances, they are altogether lighter than Vanity,</hi> Pſ. 62. 9. <hi>Solomon</hi> the Son, is of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98767:7"/> his Father <hi>David</hi>'s Mind, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Vanity of Vanities,</hi> ſaith this Preacher, <hi>Vanity of Vanities, all is Vanity.</hi> See alſo <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>All the days of his vain life, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, let us a little more diſtinctly view Man in the ſeveral Ages and Conditions of his Life.</p>
            <p>Every Age of Man is vain, and <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in a vain ſhew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Childhood.</hi> We are born into the World like wild Aſſes Colts, rude and ignorant, nay, more infirm, naked, and helpleſs than they; when we have, to the great toyl, trouble, and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Nurſes, paſt our Infancy, how light and vain, toyiſh and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable is our Childhood, how fickle and unconſtant are we, hugging and reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting in the ſame inſtant,<hi>—Hodie mihi Jupiter eſto, cras mihi truncus eris ficulus, inutile lignum;</hi> we hug that in our Boſoms to day, which we deſpiſe and are ready to throw into the Fire to morrow.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98767:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Youth</hi> is nothing but a further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Childhood, grown yet more vain, by the addition of wildneſs, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, and untractableneſs.</p>
            <p>And, what is <hi>Manhood</hi> but a little graver ſort of Childhood? There is no more real ſolidity in Bags and Lands, in order to true Happineſs, than there is in Pins and Points: There is but little more conſiſtency in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of Men, than in the Raptures of Children. He was paſt a Child, that confeſt his own Levity in theſe words, <hi>Romae Tybur amo ventoſus, Tybure Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We laugh at Children running after Butterflies, and following Crows, <hi>teſta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lutoque,</hi> with Clods and Stones. And what is building and planting, fighting and toyling, but a graver ſort of Vanity, commonly attended with a great deal of Sin and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98767:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Old-Age</hi> is Childhood of the ſecond Edition, and that oftentimes <hi>auctior,</hi> much augmented, for this frequently adds Moroſity to Vanity, and Wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Unſatisfiedneſs.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Decrepit Age,</hi> what is it but the meer Carcaſe of Man, Life drawn off to a <hi>caput mortuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every Condition of Men is alſo Vanity.</p>
            <p>Rich men indeed do think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſomething real; they ſure are more than a ſhew, they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial parts of the Creation, they therefore call their Eſtates <hi>Subſtance;</hi> as if nothing but Riches were ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial: But indeed, theſe Riches are ſo far from being Subſtance, that they are in Scripture-phraſe a kind of a <hi>Non-Ens;</hi> the Spirit of God does not allow them ſo much as a Being, before a man can well ſay they are, they are gone, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 5. Wilt thou ſet thine Eyes upon that which is not? For Riches certainly make themſelves
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98767:9"/> Wings, they fly away as an Eagle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven. Our Saviour indeed ranks Riches amongſt the <hi>leaſt</hi> of good things, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 10, 11. <hi>He that is faithful in that which is leaſt, &amp;c.</hi> and then he explains himſelf, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>If therefore ye have not been faithful in the unrighteous Mammon, who will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to your truſt the true Riches?</hi> But <hi>Solomon</hi> goes further, and diſparages them much more now, by diſcarding them out of the number of <hi>Beings, Wilt thou ſet thine Eyes upon that which is not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honours, Grandeur,</hi> and <hi>Pomp,</hi> what! they are but a bubble, a meer ſhadow. The Honour that is receiv'd from Men is but <hi>popularis aura,</hi> the Breath of the People, and that commonly a ſtinking Breath too, proceeding from Inwards corrupted and putrid, which is the rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Conſtitution of all thoſe, who, as the Apoſtle phraſes it, <hi>have mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in admiration becauſe of advantage.</hi> That which we call <hi>Grandeur,</hi> and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98767:9"/> by <hi>Pomp, Acts</hi> 25. 23. the inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Penman of that Book calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with much Fancy, much Appearance. It could not have been more fitly tranſlated, than by the words in the Text, with a <hi>vain ſhew:</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> uſes a word much like it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Faſhion of this World: As if all ſublunary things were nothing but Apparitions. A Scepter has really no more ſubſtance in it than an ordinary walking-Staff; fine and coſtly Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel are but a ſhew, and indeed for that end are they moſtly made and wore. A ſplendid Retinue is a fine Shew too, but it is a vain one, to maintain them and command them is more Coſt and Trouble than Worſhip: And the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ragged or leathern Saint that goes abroad continually with his Lifeguard of Angels, thoſe menial and miniſtring Servants of the Almighty is better guarded. What a vain Shew was <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>'s Royal Apparel, when it could not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98767:10"/> ſtave off the Lice and Vermin from eating him up alive? What a vain ſhew was the Goſpel-Rich-man's Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and fine Linnen, which could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſerve him from Death nor Hell; when <hi>Lazarus,</hi> notwithſtanding his Rags and Sores, has a Convoy of Angels into the Boſom of <hi>Abraham?</hi> And is not a Table richly furniſh'd with coſtly Diſhes and variety of delicious Fare a vain ſhew, when it ſerves no more for Health, nor the ſtrengthening of the Conſtitution, than the Prophet's Cake and Cruiſe of Water, in the ſtrength of which he travell'd forty days and forty nights, to <hi>Horeb, the mount of Gad,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19. 7. King <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> is the moſt competent Judge in this caſe of any man that ever liv'd; for, beſides the great Ingenuity he had to contrive, and the vaſt Power and Wealth he had to purchaſe all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the Sons of men, (ſuch as ſtately Houſes, fruitful Vineyards, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Orchards and Gardens, abounding
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98767:10"/> with all ſort of Fruits, Pools of Water, Servants, and Maidens, great and ſmall Cattel, Men-ſingers and Women-ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as you may read in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.) I ſay he not only had all theſe things, and many more, but alſo a vaſt largeneſs of Soul, and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom put into him from above, beyond all men upon Earth, whereby he was able to make a right eſtimate, and give a right Judgment of things, and yet after all this, paſſes this Verdict upon them all, they were all <hi>Vanity and vexation of Spirit, Eccleſ.</hi> 2. 11, 15, 17, 19.—And now having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that the Rich and the Grandees of the World, with all their Wealth and Grandeur, do walk in a vain ſhew, it is no great matter for ſpeaking of the Poor, for if the Rich be Vanity, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Poor are <hi>lighter than vanity;</hi> they ſtand for Cyphers in the World, whereas the Rich ſeem to make ſome Figure: Poor men are the Picture of men, without the Reſpect of men.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98767:11"/> There is no Advantage (alas!) for which men ſhould have their perſons in admiration. Where is the man that honours God in a poor man? Where is the man that regards or reverences an immortal Soul, if the ſame happen to be <hi>caskt</hi> up in an unſeemly Body, eſpecially if that alſo be <hi>hoop'd</hi> in filthy Rags? Let the poor man be induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and laborious, he is therefore va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued as an Ox or an Aſs is valued, and no more: Let him be ſtout and coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, he ſhall meet with no Preferment but what the valiant <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> met with, to be ſet in the fore-front of the Battel: Nay, let him be wiſe and ingenious, ſo wiſe as to <hi>preſerve the Iſland,</hi> ſo wiſe as to <hi>deliver the City,</hi> yet he ſhall be rewarded as <hi>Solomon</hi>'s poor wiſe man was, in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 15. the poor man's Wiſdom is deſpiſed, and his Words are not heard.</p>
            <p>Men in a <hi>conjugal state</hi> walk in a vain ſhew, moleſted with Family Cares, diſtracted with domeſtick ill
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98767:11"/> Accidents or Broils, and a man is at variance with his Father, the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with her Mother, the Daughter-in-law with her Mother-in-law, and a man's Enemies are frequently thoſe of his own Houſe; there is either Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Undutifulneſs, Idleneſs, Profuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Unagreeableneſs of Tempers, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsfulneſs of Undertakings, or one thing or other, that imbitters that ſtate alſo. At beſt it is but a poor and a mean Union, in compariſon of what the rational Creature is capable of.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Single Life</hi> is no leſs moleſted with Deſires, than the <hi>Conjugal</hi> is with Cares; yea, this does with as much Vanity ſeek to get into the Net as the other to get out of it. If that Precept of the Apoſtle's, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 27. <hi>(Art thou bound to a Wife, ſeek not to be looſed: Art thou looſed from a Wife, ſeek not a Wife;)</hi> were to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to theſe times (as I ſuppoſe it is not) I believe it would be as hard a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98767:12"/> Command to obſerve as any in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> are not exempted from Vanity. King <hi>Solomon</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the vanity and emptineſs of things more than any man: Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, a man of Sorrows, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Grief, wore a Crown wholly made up of Thorns. But I ſuppoſe there is no man upon Earth wears a Crown, but there are Thorns in it: If they be ſevere in ruling, they will be feared, and conſequently hated; if gentle and merciful, they will be contemn'd and diſobey'd: If they make chargeable Wars, perhaps they may get the Necks of their Enemies, but then they loſe the Hearts of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: If they be peaceable or coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they may poſſibly preſerve the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their Subjects, but then they betray their Liberty and Eſtates, and make them a Prey to foreign Princes. In a word, all Crowns are lin'd with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98767:12"/> Cares, and edg'd with Fears, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps an ordinary Felt ſits eaſier upon the Head. At beſt, mens ruling over one another, whether they be Kings or other inferior Maſters, is but a ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, a ſhew of Rule; the meaneſt Saint whom Chriſt Jeſus hath waſhed in his Blood, and made <hi>a King and a Prieſt to God and the Father,</hi> has a more real, glorious, durable Dominion than they upon that account.</p>
            <p>When we conſider the wiſe <hi>Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors</hi> and profound <hi>Stateſmen</hi> upon Earth, and how often and ſtrangely they are hallucinated, baffled, and infatuated, we cannot but ſay they walk in a <hi>vain ſhew.</hi> Let <hi>Achitophel</hi> the <hi>Gibonite</hi> bear witneſs for this ſort of men, whoſe Counſel was overthrown by <hi>Huſhas,</hi> and himſelf by a Halter. If you will, you may help out his Teſtimony by the Examples of ſome late Judges and great Miniſters of State of thoſe amongſt our ſelves. How often have we ſeen theſe men falling by the fury of an enraged
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98767:13"/> People, whom they had for ſome time ridden, and been made a Sacrifice to thoſe to whom they had been a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fooliſh</hi> and <hi>ignorant</hi> look like Men, when indeed they are excelled by <hi>the Ox that knows his owner, and the Aſs that knows his Maſter's Crib, Iſ.</hi> 1. 3. The Pſalmiſt therefore joyns theſe two together, <hi>Pſal</hi> 73. 22. <hi>So fooliſh was I, and ignorant, I was as a beaſt before thee. Sine doctrina vita, eſt quaſi mortis imago,</hi> without Wiſdom men may rather be ſaid to be dead than alive.</p>
            <p>The <hi>wiſe</hi> and the <hi>learned</hi> walk in a vain ſhew; they trouble their Heads with many Thoughts, and diſquiet themſelves in vain, ſeeking to come to the Knowledge of many things, and the Cauſes of things, which they ſhall never attain to, and give themſelves a great deal of Torment to little or no purpoſe. If they do find out ſome things, they find them out to their coſt, and to their grief; <hi>He that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98767:13"/> 
               <hi>Knowledge encreaſeth Sorrow;</hi> he comes to know many things which afterwards he could wiſh he had never known. Our Mother <hi>Eve</hi> coveted to know Good and Evil, and ſo ſhe did, but it was ſorely to her Coſt, and to ours too; in her much Wiſdom ſhe found much Grief, which is entayled upon Us her Poſterity to this day. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Much ſtudy is a wearineſs of the fleſh, Eccl.</hi> 12. 12. That you will ſay is Vanity; yea, but there is Vexation alſo added to it; for, Would it not vex any man, to ſtudy hard only to know what abundance of things there are that he is guilty of?</p>
            <p>The <hi>idle, ſlothful,</hi> and <hi>unconcern'd,</hi> walk in a vain ſhew, if indeed they may be ſaid to walk at all; theſe are unprofitable Burdens to the Earth,<hi>—Numeri ſunt fruges conſumere nati;</hi> They only ſerve for tale, to make up a Number, and devour the Fruits of the Earth; they are aſleep all their days,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98767:14"/> and what is a man good for when he is aſleep?</p>
            <p>The <hi>active, brisk,</hi> and <hi>luſty</hi> walks in a <hi>vain ſhew;</hi> he is up late and early, makes a buſtle and clatter in the World, diſquiets himſelf and all his Neighbors, defrauds his Carcaſs, troubles his Houſe with reſtleſs Motion and Buſineſs, and all this is but as Childrens ſweating and running after a painted Butterflye; he is alwaies catching at ſomething or other, in which he is commonly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, and cannot catch it; and if he do happen to catch it, he opens his Hand to view it, and behold, it is a Flye.</p>
            <p>Bad men are but like men, even as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who had the Heart of a Beaſt, under the Shape of a Man.</p>
            <p>Yea indeed, and Good men too, in this World, walk in a <hi>vain ſhew.</hi> How ignorant of many things are the wiſeſt of men? How uncertain and fickle in their Reſolutions? how uneven in their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98767:14"/> Tempers? how ebbing and flowing in their Devotions, are the Beſt of men in this World?</p>
            <p>And although Religion be ſomething ſolid, real, and ſubſtantial, yet it is but a ſhadow of what is to come. The beſt men are but like good men in this World. It is but a kind of typical Religion that we have here. What a ſcant Reſemblance is the holieſt Life upon Earth, to the Life of the other World? We rather make a ſhew of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming religious Duties, than perform them. As Angels ſometimes make a ſhew of eating and drinking, and ſitting and walking, and doing as we do, ſo we make a ſhew of ſerving and praiſing God, and doing as they do. This Knowledge of ours is but ſeeing in a Glaſs, like a Fable or Parable, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the intuition and viſion of the other World. Our Love is but like a going Fire, in compariſon of the Ardours and Amours of that World. As men laugh at little Children when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98767:15"/> they meaſure heights, ſo ſhall we here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after diſdainfully look back upon our dwarfiſh ſtature of this preſent World. The whole Life of the beſt man upon Earth, is but a Dream in compariſon of that ſtate that we ſhall be in when we awake in the Reſurrection. Read 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every man walketh in a vain ſhew. Walks,</hi> I told you, according to the Hebrew Idiom, is as much as <hi>lives</hi> or <hi>converſes,</hi> and comprehends whatſoever a man <hi>is, has,</hi> or <hi>does.</hi> I come now therefore to ſpeak particularly to theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It relates to what he is. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man is but a Shew, a Reſemblance, a kind of an Apparition. <hi>Tſelem,</hi> the word in the Text, ſignifies the Image or Reſemblance of a Body, which doth not exiſt truly and really, but in the Fancy only. Thus the Pſalmiſt uſes it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 20. <hi>As a dream when one awaketh, ſo, O Lord, when thou awakeſt, thou ſhalt deſpiſe their image; i. e.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98767:15"/> them who are rather a Reſemblance of ſomething, than truly or really any thing. To the ſame purpoſe ſpeaks <hi>Sophocles,</hi> in his <hi>Ajax,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> We mortal men are nothing more than Images or light Shadows. Man is a Shadow, as to any Reality or Subſtantialneſs; and alſo as to duration, he is fickle and ſlitting, evanid as a Vapour, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 14. as a Bubble, as a Perſon that comes upon the Stage, and repreſents a King, or a Peer, or a Peaſant, for a ſhort ſpace, and then diſappears. He is a Flower, a pretty thing to look on, for a time, but <hi>heunimium breves roſae.</hi> Alas, how ſhort liv'd are Roſes! Man cometh forth like a Flower, that is <hi>ſweet</hi> and is out down; that is <hi>ſad, Job</hi> 14. 2. yea, he fleeth as a ſhadow, and continueth not. The eloquent Prophet uſes the ſame elegant compariſon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 6. <hi>The voice ſaid. Cry; and he ſaid, What ſhall I cry? All fleſh is Graſs, and all the</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98767:16"/> 
               <hi>goodlineſs thereof as a flower of the field: The graſs withereth, the flower fadeth, becauſe the ſpirit of the Lord bloweth upon it; ſurely the people is graſs:</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> applys the compariſon to Rich men, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 10. 11. <hi>As the flower of the graſs he ſhall paſs away; for the ſun is no ſooner riſen with a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heat; but it withereth the graſs, and the flower thereof falleth, and the grace of the faſhion of it periſheth, ſo alſo ſhall the rich man fade away in his ways:</hi> But the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> applies it to them in particular, and alſo to all in general, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 24. <hi>For all fleſh is as graſs, and all the glory of man as the flower of graſs; the graſs withereth, and the flower thereof falleth away.</hi> The Heathen Sages uſed the ſame compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Poor Man is no better than a Garment fretted and half eaten with Moths, which, you know, is then no better than a Rag; he dwelleth in a Houſe made of Clay, whoſe Foundation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98767:16"/> is in the Duſt, and is cruſh'd before the Moths, <hi>Job</hi> 4. 19. he conſumeth as a rotten thing, as a Garment that is Moth-eaten, <hi>Job</hi> 13. 27. The greateſt Bravery of Man is but like a Moth, a thing that men alwaies kill by cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; it needs no Knife to ſhed its Blood, no Halter to ſtrangle it, no Ax to behead it, no, nor ſo much as a Womans Nail to diſpatch it; do but catch it and cruſh it, and it ceaſes to be; <hi>Pſ.</hi> 39. 11. <hi>When thou with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes doſt correct man for iniquity, thou makeſt his beauty to conſume away like a moth: Surely every man is vanity.</hi> They ſpeak of the Apples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> fair and beautiful to look upon, but touch them and they drop into Aſhes. Such a comely Vanity is Man, do but touch him, and he drops to Duſt in his Body, and his Soul takes its flight into another World; ſo vain a thing is Man, as to his <hi>duration.</hi> But this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Man's frailty, flittingneſs, and undurableneſs, is ſo well known to all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98767:17"/> men, and ſo readily confeſs'd by all, that I think I need not further inſiſt upon it, though it opens to any man a great Field of Diſcourſe, at the very firſt view. A little therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſume the former Argument concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Man's ſeeming to be ſomething, when indeed he is nothing. I ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there is no ſolidity, no conſiſtency in Man.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Beauty</hi> is but a <hi>Paint,</hi> a <hi>Varniſh,</hi> in compariſon of true and ſubſtantial A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miableneſs, and falls as far ſhort of it as a patcht and painted Face falls ſhort of of the native lovelineſs and ſweetneſs, which is to be diſcerned in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of a pure uncorrupted Virgin, or the Virginity of a Damask Roſe The Beauty of this corruptible Body is no more to be compared to the ſweetneſs and luſtre of the glorified Body, than <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Sun-burnt Face, when he was Shepherd to <hi>Jethro</hi> the <hi>Midianite,</hi> was to be compared to his ſhining Face, when he came down from the Mount
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98767:17"/> of <hi>God,</hi> and was fain to put a Veil upon it, that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> might behold him; or indeed, no more than the gliſtering of a <hi>Glow-worm</hi> is to be compared to the bightneſs of the <hi>Sun</hi> at mid-day.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Strength,</hi> alas! it is but weakneſs and rottenneſs. Men, eſpecially young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, are apt to glory in their ſtrength, and to pride <hi>themſelves</hi> in their running, riding, wreſtling, and fighting; whereas the ableſt, ſtouteſt, ſtrongeſt of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men, is a meer Child, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of one of the Angels of God, yea, or of one Devil either; yea, I may add, in compariſon of any Child of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; for, theſe Bodies of ours are buried in Weakneſs, but ſhall be raiſed in Power, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 43. Beſides, this Strength of his, which he pretends to, has no duration with it, it vaniſhes away in a moment, and Man as a <hi>rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thing conſumeth, as a garment that is moth-eaten, Job</hi> 13. 28. Who could chuſe but pitty <hi>Peter,</hi> ſtretching out
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98767:18"/> his Hands to be bound and carried away whither he would not, who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſeen him girding himſelf, and walking whitherſoever he would; or <hi>Sampſon</hi> grinding in the Priſon, who had formerly ſeen him carrying away the Gates of <hi>Gaza</hi> upon his Shoulders, Doors, Poſts, and Bar and all? Who, I ſay, can chuſe but bewail the vain ſhew that the ſtrong man makes, who ſees his Iron Sinews become like Straw, and his Braſs Bones turn'd into rotten Wood, as the Almighty loftily expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it in the <hi>41ſt</hi> of <hi>Job.</hi> And as his Beauty is but a Paint or Varniſh, his Strength but Infirmity and Rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo</p>
            <p>His <hi>Valonr</hi> is but a <hi>Flouriſh,</hi> and a meer Vapour. The bombaſt words, and prophane brags of the Philiſtine-Champion <hi>Goliah,</hi> who defied the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the living God, and diſdain'd the little Champion of <hi>Iſrael, Come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and I will give thy fleſh to the fowls of the air, and to the beaſts of the</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98767:18"/> 
               <hi>field,</hi> prov'd to be nothing but the blaſphemous Bravado of an uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed Tongue, which was preſently ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenc'd, and carried away with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Head that contain'd it, and his mighty brandiſh'd Blade was wrapp'd up in a Clout, and laid behind the Ephod in obſcurity. Beſides, this Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Proweſs will, in a ſhort time, be turn'd into ſuch Cowardiſe and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtordlineſs, that it will not dare to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, no, not ſo much as the Worms, that will crawl and feed upon the valiant <hi>Hero,</hi> and then he that ſees it will wonder, and ſay, <hi>Loe, here's all that remains of great Saladine;</hi> or, Loe here that Limb of a man, who is now a Worm, and no Man. His Valour is but a Flouriſh and a meer Vapour.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Conſtancy</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> is but a ſhew of Stedfaſtneſs: Ten thouſand Inſtances do tell us how frail, fickle, and deceitful the Affections, Words, Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Oaths and Vows of the Children of Men are; they love to day and hate to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98767:19"/> morrow, and the Hatred with which they hate, perhaps, is greater than the Love wherewith they loved. <hi>Ammon</hi> is ſick for his Siſter <hi>Tamar</hi> to day, to morrow, having ſpoil'd her of her Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he is as ſick of her; <hi>Ariſe, be gone,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 15. And again, <hi>Put now this woman out from me, and bolt the door after her, v.</hi> 19. <hi>Though all the world ſhould deny thee,</hi> cries <hi>Peter</hi> to his Maſter, <hi>yet will not I deny thee, I will dye with thee rather, Mat.</hi> 26. 33, 35. But before morning his note is changed, <hi>ver.</hi> 72. <hi>I know not the man:</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 74. <hi>He began to curſe and ſwear, ſaying, I know not the man. Peter,</hi> I warrant ye, thought he had a ſubſtantial ſtedfaſtneſs, but ſee what a vain ſhew it proved to be. It ſeems, by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> that the Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Promiſes that are made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Fleſh, <hi>i. e.</hi> according to men in the Fleſh, are doubtful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, on and off; they are <hi>yea, yea,</hi> and <hi>nay, nay,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 17. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98767:19"/> there is ſo much lightneſs and unſteddineſs in humane Minds and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and ſo much variableneſs in their Affections, that their Conſtancy is no more to be compared to ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Steddineſs, than the levity of a Feather to the ſtability of a Mountain.—Beſides, let men be never ſo firm, faithful, and conſtant in their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, alas, their time comes preſently, when all their Thoughts periſh: Let them be never ſo juſt, punctual, and true to their Word, their Breath, and with that all their Words, will vaniſh into Air in a ſhort time; ſo vain a thing is Man: <hi>Surely every man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Patience</hi> is but a ſhew of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, mingled with a great deal of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, and ſoon worn out too. <hi>Ye have heard of the patience of Job,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle <hi>James;</hi> yes, ſo we have, and we have heard of his Impatience too, witneſs the third Chapter of his Hiſtory, when <hi>he opened his mouth,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98767:20"/> 
               <hi>and curſed his day;—</hi>(read the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter). We have heard of the Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Moſes</hi> too, who was the meekeſt man upon Earth, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. 3. but we have heard of his Paſſion too, and raſh Anger, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 32, 33. <hi>It went ill with Moſes for their ſakes, becauſe they provoked his ſpirit, ſo that he ſpake unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly with his lips.</hi> And be Man's Patience never ſo pure, it is rare to find it have its <hi>perfect Work;</hi> one Evil after another, one Battery upon the back of another, will ſhake it, if not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh it. <hi>Elijah</hi> long endured the Perverſeneſs of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Affronts and Gainſayings of <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezabel;</hi> but when word was brought him, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his good Offices, <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> would have his Head to morrow, he aroſe, and went for his Life, and prayed in the anger and anguiſh of his Spirit, that he might dye, ſaying, <hi>It is enough, now, O Lord, take away my life,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19. 4. His Succeſſor <hi>Eliſha</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently endured many Provocations and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98767:20"/> Perſecutions from that idolatrous Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in which he lived; but when the wicked and ungrateful King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for whom he had done ſo many good Offices, ſent a Meſſenger to take away his Head, he falls into a ſit of Impatience, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 6. 32. <hi>See ye how this ſon of a murderer is ſent to take away my head:</hi> And ſtill worſe, in <hi>ver.</hi> 33. he ſaid, <hi>Behold, this evil is of the Lord; what ſhould I wait for the Lord any longer? Loeſa patientia fit furor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Patience,</hi> ſo the <hi>Charity</hi> of Man upon Earth is imperfect, it is but a ſhew of Charity, in compariſon of the pure Kindneſs and Benevolence of the Angels of God, or of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of <hi>juſt men made perfect.</hi> Alas! how great an Allay, a mixture of Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, is to be found in the ſweeteſt Temper upon Earth? The Children of Men indeed, ſo far forth as they are Children of God, <hi>i. e.</hi> followers of him, are Children of Love, for <hi>God is Love.</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98767:21"/> But alas, the moſt God like, and the beſt-natur'd of them, do love but in part; they have Gall mingled with their Honey, <hi>the root that beareth gall,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> calls it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 18. is not perfectly eradicated, no, not out of the Trees that are of the Lord's own planting. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were men beloved of God and his Church, Lovers of God and of his Goſpel, great Lovers one of another, conſtant and dear Companions in Travel, in Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, in Perſecution, yet for a ſmall matter (one would think) this loving pair ſell out, and the Controverſie grew ſo hot and, fierce, that they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one from the other, when indeed they had more need to have gone to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 39.—Beſides, this very <hi>Charity,</hi> as it is imperfect, ſo it is evanid, and apt to decay, whilſt men are in this Bodily ſtate. Be it a holy Fire, kindled from above in the Souls of men, yet the very Fire of the Altar will decay, if Fuel be not adminiſtred
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98767:21"/> to it. Diſtance of Place, want of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terviews and Correſpondence, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of that which we apprehend love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, any apprehenſion of Affront, or ſo much as a Neglect, with many an other Accident, is apt to quench this Flame, or at leaſt abate the heat of the Paſſion. How often do we hear Men complaining of their conditions, which ſometimes they ſeemed well pleaſed with, Husbands ſaying to their Wives, and Wives to their Husbands, I would we had never met together; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaying to his Son, I would I had never begotten thee; and the Mother to her Daughter, Woe is me, that ever I brought thee forth; ſo poor, impure, imperfect, and unconſtant is this Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which yet certainly is the nobleſt that belongs to the human Nature.</p>
            <p>View poor Man in any of his Ages, Conditions, Qualifications, Paſſions, or the effects of them, and you will find him vain, and walking <hi>in a vain ſhew:</hi> What's his Mirth, but a light and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98767:22"/> empty Jovialty, without any real Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or ſolid Satisfaction? We may all juſtly ſay as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>I ſaid of laughter it is mad, and of mirth what doth it?</hi> What doth it indeed? for the very contrary to it is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded above it, and preferred before it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 2. <hi>It is better to go to the houſe of mourning, than to go to the houſe of feaſting:</hi> And then, <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Sorrow is better than laughter:</hi> And again, <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>The heart of the wiſe is in the houſe of mourning, but the heart of fools in the houſe of mirth:</hi> And again, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>It is better to hear the rebuke of the wiſe, than to hear the ſong of fools; for, as the crackling of thorns under a pot, ſo is the laughter of a fool;</hi> loud perhaps, but it is but a blaze, neither of any uſe, nor for any duration. And if man's <hi>Mirth</hi> be ſo vain, that even Sorrow itſelf is preferred before it, it might be worth the while to enquire wherein lies the ſolidity of <hi>Sorrow,</hi> and to ſay of this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>What doth it?</hi> For, what doth it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98767:22"/> profit a man to ſorrow for the Loſſes that he cannot retrieve, the Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he cannot amend, for things paſt that cannot be recover'd; for things preſent, that cannot be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died; for things to come, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be prevented? Sorrow is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinging of the Soul, and why ſhould Man diſquiet himſelf in vain? And how much of the ſtrength of their Souls do men miſpend in ſorrowing? They oftentimes grieve for an Evil which really was not befaln them, and oftentimes for a thing, which though it was befaln them, was not really evil. Did not old <hi>Jacob</hi> walk in a <hi>vain ſhew,</hi> when he walked heavily and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully many years, for the Death of his dear <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who was at that time Lord of all <hi>Aegypt.</hi> And ſuppoſe he had known that he was ſold into <hi>Egypt,</hi> I warrant he would nevertheleſs have grieved, although really it was no evil to <hi>Jacob</hi> that he was ſold thither. <hi>Mary</hi> was troubled that ſhe could not find
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98767:23"/> her dead Lord in the Sepulchre, when indeed it was good for her that he was riſen, and was not there: So vain, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous, and fooliſh a thing is the Mirth and the Sorrow too of the Sons of men.</p>
            <p>Poor man, Is he awake? By Seeing or Hearing he is continually betray'd, or at leaſt moleſted: He is either apt to ſpeak what he ſhould not, or ſure to hear what he would not; he is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſſolved in Pleaſure, diſtracted with Cares, or tired with Buſineſs; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vex'd with ſeeing other men do amiſs, or envies them doing well; he is either wearied with very Idleneſs, and having nothing to do, or ſurfeited with doing the ſame things over and over again, all the days of his life. He is (forſooth) ever and anon hungry or thirſty, or weary, and a great part of the waking time of his life is ſpent in relieving theſe Neceſſities.—Well then, may ſome one ſay, Commend me to <hi>Sleep,</hi> for this frees the poor Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98767:23"/> from all theſe Inconveniences. True indeed; But then (alas!) what is he good for? Then the Wiſe differs nothing from a Fool, nor the Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from a Child. As the Grave is, ſo is the Bed, and all lye down alike in both, and Sleep like Death ſweetly feeds upon them all. There is an old Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in the Schools, <hi>An proeſtat miſerum eſſe an non eſſe?</hi> One might almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret and illuſtrate it by waking and ſleeping, whether is better, to be awake and be diſquieted, or aſleep, and not to be at all. That ſo great a part of our little Age paſſes away ſo unſenſibly, and is ſpent ſo unprofitably, muſt needs trouble any wiſe man, who reflects upon it when he is awake. But, alas! there is ſomewhat worſe than Unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitableneſs in it. If it were poſſible for men to be aſleep, and yet awake at the ſame time; I mean, if we did know how our time is ſpent, and how it goes on when we are aſleep, it would add Shame to our Trouble, and Vexation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98767:24"/> to the Vanity. Many men do dream, even waking, the whole life of the greateſt part of Mankind is nothing but a Dream; but the beſt and wiſeſt of men dream ſleeping, yea, and ſo dream, as that in the morning they have cauſe with ſhame to confeſs, it was no part of their Goodneſs or Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom either. Other while poor men are affrighted with Viſions or ſtrange Apprehenſions in the night-time, ſo as that their ſleep itſelf is not ſweet unto them: The Inconveniences and Evils of the Night are ſo many, that it may well be doubted whether any man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (if a man aſleep may be ſaid to be alive) do paſs any one night of his life in that Peace and Purity as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and as becomes his noble Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>And now I am ſpeaking of Man, as to what he <hi>is,</hi> and that therein he walks in a vain ſhew. I may fitly conſider alſo what he <hi>knows,</hi> he walks in a vain ſhew as to that alſo. As his <hi>Beauty</hi> is but a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98767:24"/> Paint, his <hi>Valour</hi> but a Flouriſh, his <hi>Strength</hi> Rottenneſs, his <hi>Conſtancy, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> but a Reſemblance of ſome ſuch things, ſo indeed that wherein he is ſo very apt to glory,</p>
            <p>His <hi>Knowledge,</hi> is but a Conjecture: He thinks he knows many things, which indeed he does but gueſs at; <hi>And if any man think that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 2. To know things is properly to know the cauſes of things; and, alas! how little is there of this ſort of Knowledge, that a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt man dare pretend to? We all allow <hi>Solomon</hi> to have been a wiſe and knowing man, and yet who is there that confeſſes his Ignorance more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and frequently than he, as appears by that form of ſpeech that he ſo often uſes, <hi>Who knoweth,</hi> and <hi>who can tell? Who knoweth whether his heir ſhall be a wiſe man or a fool, Eccl.</hi> 2. 19? <hi>Who knoweth the ſpirit of a man that goeth upward, and the ſpirit of the beaſt, that</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:98767:25"/> 
               <hi>goeth downward to the earth, Eccl.</hi> 3. 21? <hi>Who knoweth what is good for man in this life, Eccl.</hi> 6. 12? <hi>Who knoweth the interpretation of a thing, Eccl.</hi> 8. 1? <hi>Who can tell a man what ſhall be after him under the ſun, Eccl.</hi> 6. 12? <hi>Who can tell him when it ſhall be, Eccl.</hi> 8. 7? <hi>And what ſhall be after him, who can tell. Eccl.</hi> 10. 14? Our knowledge of things paſt is by <hi>Tradition,</hi> of things preſent many of them by <hi>Hear-ſay,</hi> and of things to come by meer <hi>Conjecture:</hi> And is not all this very uncertain? How vaſtly do the Sentiments of the men of this Age vary from the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the men of the laſt Ages? and it is very likely, that many of the Opinions and Doctrines, both in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and Divinity, which this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Generation embraces, will in the next Age be rejected and exploded: Nay, the ſame man, in different ſtages of his own Age, and different circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his own Life, varies from himſelf. Who can chuſe but wonder
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98767:25"/> and confeſs, that <hi>man walketh in a vain ſhew,</hi> as to his Knowledge, who ſhall look into a Church in the beginning of an Age, and find it wholly <hi>Calvini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical,</hi> and look upon it again towards the end of the ſame Age, and find it almoſt wholly <hi>Arminian,</hi> or <hi>Bellarminian,</hi> the Schools then wholly <hi>Ariſtotelian,</hi> and now moſtly <hi>Carteſian.</hi> How eaſily and ſuddenly does Worldly Intereſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Minds of men, who force them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to believe certain Propoſitions or Doctrines, becauſe it is for their ſecular advantage to profeſs them. Add to this <hi>Vanity</hi> the <hi>Vexation</hi> that attends Man as to his Knowledge; this might be made out in many particulars, ſome few of which I touch'd upon before. To ſay nothing therefore of thoſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider a little the vexatious <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreſolved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> that attends the moſt ingenious and inquiſitive of the Sons of Men; and this Vexation does moſt haunt the fineſt Heads, and the tendereſt Hearts. They that are moſt conſcientious, are careful
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98767:26"/> to act judiciouſly, that their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may not condemn them, as to the things wherein they allow themſelves; which whilſt they ſeek to do, that they may approve themſelves to God, they make many Enquiries, beat their Brains, turn over their Books, ſummon all the Powers of their Souls to give a right Verdict in the caſe. In this Conteſt many poor Souls ſpend all their days, and can come to no Reſolution, but flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuate to and fro, like Waves toſſed with the contrary Winds, and never arrive at true Reſt, Reſolution, and Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mind all their life long. When after all (if after all) they ſeem to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at ſome ſatisfaction, and as King <hi>Agrippa</hi> ſays, are <hi>almoſt perſwaded,</hi> then preſently ariſes ſome Storm, ſome Blaſt from ſome Author or Argument or other, and ſhakes their not well fix'd Reſolution, ravels all again, and drives them back into the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities as before; ſo that their Minds are reſtleſs and raging, one while <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98767:26"/> another while <hi>denying,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in ſome degree <hi>doubting.</hi> And is not this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreſolvedneſs</hi> a vexatious Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, wherein men, yea, the beſt of men, do walk: Which ſo troubled the modeſt Philoſopher of old, that he cried, <hi>Hoc tantum ſcio, me nihil ſcire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A man may, upon the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rather be ſaid to ſeem to be, than to be any thing that is good.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if there be any thing ſolid or ſubſtantial in Man, it is that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he denies himſelf to be any thing, and empties himſelf of himſelf.</p>
            <p>And yet this is but very imperfect neither; for, our very Self-denyal is mingled with much Pride and Selfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whilſt we are in this poor Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim ſtate.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to conſider, that <hi>Man walketh in a vain ſhew,</hi> as to what he <hi>hath</hi> or <hi>poſſeſſeth.</hi> The Poſſeſſions of this World are but a ſhew, a ſhadow of good things, in both the forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reſpects, but empty and fleeting;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98767:27"/> they are thin and meagre, have no bulk, weight, nor ſubſtance in them, nor any conſiderable duration. In ſhort, they have neither <hi>ſolidity</hi> nor <hi>ſtability.</hi> All Earthly Poſſeſſions, even the fineſt, ſweeteſt, and braveſt of them, are cry'd up, or cry'd out on rather for Vanity, by the moſt competent Judge that ever liv'd upon Earth; read <hi>Ecc.</hi> 2. And what can be lighter and emptier than Vanity? And it is but an imaginary kind of Happineſs, which the Rich, the Honourable, the Learned, the Valiant, and Victorious do enjoy. So then both the Poſſeſſions themſelves, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light that is taken in them are both Vanity; <hi>Surely every man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Poſſeſſions themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Riches</hi> are but a ſhadow of ſome ſubſtantial and durable Good; they are but a Fancy. Abſtract them from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98767:27"/> the Love of God, ſeparate them from their End and Uſe, and they are as meer Husks, as thoſe that the Prodigal in the Parable fed upon, in compariſon of the Bread of his Father's Houſe: I ſay, ſeparate them from their End and Uſe, for what is a Coffer of Gold bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a heap of Counters, if no body may touch it nor uſe it? What is a rich <hi>Palace</hi> better than a heap of Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh, or a Caſtle in the Air, if no man may be permitted to inhabit it? What is coſtly <hi>Apparel</hi> better than rotten Rags, if no one may be ſuffer'd to put it on? Well, ſuppoſe this Wealth to be us'd, it is a thouſand to one but it is abus'd and miſpent upon vain Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, unprofitable Curioſities, or need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Superfluities. The Paint and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of a Houſe render it never the more ſafe nor ſtrong: The coſtly Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel of Scarlet and Velvet keep the Body no warmer than the Prophet's <hi>Girdle of Leather,</hi> or the Baptiſt's <hi>Coat of Camels Hair.—</hi>Again, abſtract
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98767:28"/> Worldly Wealth and Riches from the Love of God; <hi>i. e.</hi> Suppoſe a man to have much Gold and no Grace, much Wealth and no Virtue, much of Earth in his Hands and nothing of Heaven in his Heart; ſuppoſe his Riches to be gotten by Fraud or Violence, by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Cunning or Covetouſneſs; ſuppoſe them to be given him for a Curſe and a Snare, and an aggravation of his Condemnation, does not this man walk in as vain a ſhew as thoſe Slaves that are continually emyloyed in the Mines of Silver and Gold, carrying many a heavy load for the ſervice of their Maſters, themſelves all the while remaining miſerable Slaves for all that?—Again, compare this Worldly Wealth with the true Riches, with Grace and Glory, which do enrich and adorn the Mind; and, what ſhall we call it then? Let the Prophet ſpeak for me, and tell you, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 6. it is thick Clay; <hi>Woe to him that ladeth himſelf with thick clay.</hi> Thick Clay! this is Subſtance
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98767:28"/> indeed, but it is dirty and naſty for a Soul to wallow in, fitter for a Swine than for a Soul. Let another Prophet ſpeak, <hi>Zech.</hi> 9. 3. <hi>Tyrus heaped up ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as the duſt; and fine gold as the mire of the streets.</hi> Or, let holy <hi>Job</hi> ſpeak, <hi>Job</hi> 27. 16. <hi>He heaps up ſilver as the duſt, and prepares raiment as the clay.—</hi>Nay again, we will ſuppoſe that Riches be made uſe of, yea, and good uſe of, (which is the beſt that can be ſuppos'd) yet when Goods encreaſe, they are encreas'd that eat them; and <hi>What good is there to the owners thereof, ſaving the beholding of them with their eyes, Eccl.</hi> 5. 11? In a word, there is a Curſe entail'd upon all that covet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Riches, which does unavoidably light upon them all, <hi>viz.</hi> they ſhall go on ſtill hungring and gaping after more, and ſhall never be filled, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>He that loveth ſilver ſhall not not be ſatisfied with ſilver, nor he that loveth abundance with encreaſe.</hi> And then he adds, as with good reaſon he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98767:29"/> might, <hi>This is alſo vanity.</hi> The worth of theſe things is placed principally in the Fancies of Men. You have heard perhaps of ſome Rich men, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a melancholick Diſtemper have fancied themſelves to be very Poor, and I wonder then what good their Riches do them. And I have read of a poor man, who in his merry Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy would ſtand upon the Shore and clap his Hands, and laugh and rejoyce at the coming in of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Ships, fancying them all to be his own. And I wonder what he could have done more, if they had been all his own indeed: And is not that a Vanity, that a man may fancy himſelf into, or out of, when he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes?—Beſides, in the latter ſence, theſe Riches are Vanity too, becauſe they ſoon vaniſh; <hi>They take to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wings, and fly away,</hi> as <hi>Solomon,</hi> expreſſes it, yea, and that ſwiftly and irrecoverably, as an Eagle towards Heaven. Now theſe Wings are made
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98767:29"/> up of many ſorts of Feathers, ſuch as Thieves, Knaves, violent Enemies and Oppreſſors, falſe and deceitful Friends, Fire, Sword, Wind and Tempeſts, Suits at Law, Forgery, Perjury, Moths and Ruſt, and I know not how many more. I will quit this point, leaving with you that good and grave Advice of your beſt Friend, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 19, 20. <hi>Lay not up for your ſelves treaſures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, but lay up for your ſelves trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in Heaven, where neither moth nor ruſt doth corrupt, and where thieves do not break through nor ſteal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friends</hi> are a Worldly Poſſeſſion, highly prized by ſome, and indeed needed by all: They are a very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Poſſeſſion, a very great, but a very rare Treaſure. True Friends are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom acquir'd, hardly kept, and with great Grief parted with. There are ſo many things go to the making up of a true and rightly-accompliſh'd Friend, that it may well be doubted, whether every thouſandth man in the World
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98767:30"/> have one. They that live in populous places have many Neighbors, the Rich have many Servants, the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent have many Auditors, the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned have many Pupils and Clients, the Honourable and the Worſhipful have many Flatterers, and perhaps not one of theſe has a true Friend; for neither Affinity, Riches, Eloquence, Learning, Honour, or Grandeur can purchaſe true Friendſhip: And indeed, there are few men in this depraved ſtate of Mankind fit to make Friends of. If a man be fooliſh or falſe, if he be covetous or ſelfiſh, if he be cowardly, proud, or paſſionate, if he be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſelf-concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, humerous, inconſtant, or an intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſelf-lover, he cannot be made a Friend of. And (alas!) where is the man that is not ſome of all this?</p>
            <p>To <hi>keep</hi> a Friend is no leſs difficult than to <hi>get</hi> one. The tenderer any part of the Body is, the ſooner it is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98767:30"/> hurt, and the eaſilier-offended. Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is a tender and delicate thing, and eaſily grieved; every ſmall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, Paſſion, or ſo much as Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, is apt to wound, if not to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it, and Friendſhip, when it comes to be ſuſpected is half broken. If no man can be properly called a Friend, but ſuch an one as <hi>Solomon</hi> deſcribes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. 17. <hi>Who loveth at all times,</hi> I doubt there will very few be found, ſo inconſtant is all human Love, ſo apt to be abated, if not aboliſh'd. <hi>Is this thy kindneſs to thy friend,</hi> ſaid <hi>Abſalom</hi> jeeringly to <hi>Huſhai,</hi> becauſe he did not willingly go with his Friend <hi>David</hi> into Baniſhment, <hi>why wenteſt thou not with thy friend,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 17? How often have all men cauſe to reflect as tartly upon their pretended Friends, upon the account of ſome Commiſſion or Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or other? Is this your Kindneſs to your Friend? Why did you not go hither or thither? Why did you
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98767:31"/> not do this or that? Why did you not ſpeak thus or thus for your Friend? Friends were ordain'd for a time of Adverſity, but (alas!) they will not abide it, few of them are Adverſity-proof.—But, at beſt, Friends muſt part. If they have lived lovingly and faithfully all their days, (which is rare to be found) yet Death, worſe and crueller than the Whiſperer that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of, will <hi>ſeparate the chiefeſt Friends</hi> that ever lov'd or liv'd together, and then behold what Lamentation and Mourning; <hi>The beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Iſrael is ſlain; O Jonathan, thou waſt ſlain in thy high places: I am diſtreſſed for thee, my brother Jonathan; very pleaſant haſt thou been unto me, thy love to me was wonderful, paſſing the love of women,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. The taking away of ſuch a Friend, is like the rending of Limb from Limb, or the violent tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Soul from Body. <hi>Oh the deſire of mine Eyes,</hi> cries one; <hi>Oh the delight</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:98767:31"/> 
               <hi>of my Soul,</hi> cries another; how art thou taken away as with a ſtroke, and haſt left me to grapple with the Misfortunes of an injurious and vexatious World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone! <hi>Surely every man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Children</hi> are a pleaſant Poſſeſſion. With what Ardours of Soul, with what unparallel'd Raviſhments are theſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd? Theſe are Images of our ſelves, nay, <hi>Parts</hi> indeed rather than <hi>Pictures;</hi> theſe are, in a ſound Sence, <hi>Bone of our Bone, and Fleſh of our Fleſh;</hi> in them we enjoy our ſelves whilſt we live; in them we live when we are dead. Well, all this, and a great deal more may be ſaid concerning this Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of human Nature, but does not poor Man <hi>walk in a vain ſhew</hi> as to this Poſſeſſion too? After they are begotten and born in Sin and Sorrow, and nurſt up with much Wakefulneſs and Weariſomneſs, they become pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98767:32"/> Playfellows, and enchant the fond Parents with their ſweet Smiles and liſping Rhetorick, and every little Trick, that is any thing akin to Wit or Ingenuity. In the midſt of theſe Charms, it may be, comes ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſter or other, and breaks a Leg or an Arm, an Ague, or the Worms, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prave the Conſtitution, or the Small Pox, and quite ſpoyl the Complexion; nay, it is great odds, but ſome of theſe prove fatal and mortal, and the Child never lives to ſee itſelf a Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but is quite taken off the Stage of the World, before it was able to take a turn upon it, or knew how to <hi>walk before the Living:</hi> Oh then, what bitter lamentation, mourning, and weeping is there! If the Child be ſick, we have <hi>David</hi> faſting, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Earth, and in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of his Soul refuſing to eat Bread, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 16, 17. If the Child dye, then you have <hi>Rachel</hi> weeping and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98767:32"/> wailing, ready to tear her Hair, yea, her very Heart, and refuſing to be comforted, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 15.—Well, but ſuppoſe they eſcape this firſt Rencounter, and grow up to be young Men and Women, then behold what Perplexity follows, about their Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and diſpoſing of them into a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled Condition in the World; what perpetual Care and Fear for them, leſt they ſhould be infected, inſnared, depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, leſt they ſhould take <hi>bad ways,</hi> or come to any <hi>bad end.</hi> Alas! how many prove to be the greateſt Heart-breaking to their Parents, in their Manhood, who were the deſire of their Eyes, and delight of their Hearts in their Childhood? They pleaſe our Eyes when they are Children, and when they are grown up, are oftentimes as Smoak to our Eyes. We play with them at Two or Three, and it may be weep over them at Twenty or Thirty: We dandle them in our Hands at firſt, and afterwards wring our
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98767:33"/> Hands over them. Children are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſaid to be the Staff of their Parents Old-Age, and yet how often do we ſee Men beaten with this Staff of their Old-Age? If they prove bad and uſeleſs, we are ready to wiſh we had never been the Inſtruments of their Being. If they prove good and uſeful, oh then how are we tormented with Fear, leſt they ſhould dye before us, leſt the Encreaſe of our Houſe ſhould fall in the Flower of their Age. If they be wicked, and yet live on, it is but to conſume the Parents Eyes, and grieve their Hearts: If they be cut off in their Wickedneſs, Enemies to God, and unprepared for another World, then, <hi>O my ſon Abſalom! O Abſalom my ſon, my ſon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. ult. If they be good and uſeful, and yet cut off in the flower of their Age, then there is the greateſt Complaint, and the bittereſt Cry of all, <hi>I will go down into the grave unto my ſon mourning, Gen.</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:98767:33"/> 36. 35. If Children dye before the Parents, there is a ſad loſs and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; if they ſurvive, yet the Parents are not free from Fears or Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, ſo long as they live, <hi>For who knoweth whether he ſhall be a wiſe man or a fool that ſhall be after me, yet ſhall he have rule over all my labour? This is alſo Vanity,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 19.</p>
            <p>Yet on the other hand, As to be full of Children is to be full of Folly, Fear, Care, and Anxiety, ſo to be <hi>Childleſs,</hi> is to be full of Envy and Diſcontent, and Unſatisfiedneſs: This is alſo <hi>Vanity. There is one alone, and there is not a ſecond,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon, he hath neither Child nor Brother; q. d.</hi> he has no body to take care of, or to provide for, <hi>yet there is no end of all his labour, neither is his eye ſatisfied with riches, neither ſaith he, for whom do I labour, and bereave my ſoul of</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98767:34"/> 
               <hi>good?</hi> This is alſo Vanity, yea, it is a ſore Travel, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. 8. See the grievous Vanity of Humane Life in that one Inſtance of <hi>Rachel;</hi> before ſhe had Children, ſhe was carried away with Envy and Anger, <hi>Give me chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or elſe I dye, Gen.</hi> 30. 1. Well, ſhe has them, but take them away, and then ſhe is tranſported with bitter Grief and inconſolable Sorrow; ſhe weeps for her Children, and would not be comforted for her Children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not. To have Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren puts us to trouble to get Eſtates for them, whilſt we live: To have none, puts us to trouble how to diſpoſe of our Eſtates when we dye.<hi>—Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what ſhall we ſay of <hi>Victory</hi> and Succeſs in Warlike Actions? Why, I ſay, it is a pretty kind of Pageantry, a vain ſhew, like all the reſt. What a rare ſight is it to ſee one man beat
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98767:34"/> another? a rare thing for a rational Soul to contemplate, two ſilly Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals ſtriving upon the Stage of the World, and one too hard for the other. That which one man carries away from another is but a ſhadow of Victory, in compariſon of that Victory which the diligent and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Soul gets over itſelf and its own Paſſions and vile Affections: And in a ſhort time, the brave victorious <hi>Hero,</hi> that now carries his Head ſo high, muſt lay down Head and Hands and all, at the Feet of Worms and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</p>
            <p>And what ſhall we ſay of <hi>Reputation</hi> and Credit? <hi>Solomon</hi> indeed ſays, <hi>A good name is better than precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 1. Well, be it ſo; yet precious Ointment itſelf is but a Vanity: Let but a few dead Flyes fall into it, and it makes it ſend forth a ſtinking Savour: So doth a little
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98767:35"/> Folly, a ſmall Miſtake, quite ſpoil the man that is in much Reputation for Wiſdom and Honour, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 1. One falſe Step taken, one Error com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, one malignant <hi>But</hi> clapt in, ſpoils the Beauty and Braveneſs of a man's Character. <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> Prince had a brave Character, <hi>Naaman Captain of the hoſt of the King of Syria, was a great man with his maſter, and honourable, becauſe by him the Lord had given deliverance unto Syria; he was alſo a mighty man in valour.</hi> This was a noble Character indeed, and yet all blurr'd with one miſchievous <hi>But, But he was a leper,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 5. 1. What pity was it that this fair Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traicture ſhould all be daſh'd with one Blot, <hi>But he was a leper?</hi> This very good Report or Reputation is ſo enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Vanity, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> found there was need to watch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, as well as againſt bad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 8. It is ſo vain a ſhew,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98767:35"/> that our Saviour tells us, that the more univerſal and uncontroulable it is, the more dangerous and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous it is, <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 26. <hi>Woe unto you when all men ſhall ſpeak well of you.</hi> The Approbation and Praiſe which is ſolid, and makes men happy, is <hi>of God,</hi> and not <hi>of men,</hi> as the Apoſtle phraſes it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 29.</p>
            <p>In a word, whatever Solidity or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantialneſs may be fancied to be in any of theſe Worldly Poſſeſſions (as certainly ſome do bid fairer for it than others, yet their flittingneſs, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhingneſs, and want of Duration, renders them a vain ſhew after all. The things, all the things that are ſeen are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, temporary; but the things that are not ſeen, theſe are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 8.</p>
            <p>I told you, that both the Poſſeſſions themſelves, and the Delight and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that is taken in them, are a vain
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98767:36"/> ſhew. Having ſpoken to the firſt of theſe, I now come to ſpeak a word or two to the latter, <hi>viz.</hi> the Delight of the Sons of men do take in theſe Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions. I am wont to diſtinguiſh between <hi>Poſſeſſions</hi> and <hi>Enjoyments,</hi> though in ordinary Diſcourſe men are apt to confound them; for I can make good theſe two Propoſitions, <hi>viz. That many men poſſeſs many things which they do not enjoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the covetous Worldly-minded man poſſeſſes Bags of Gold &amp; Silver, which he dares not touch, except it be to count it, and lay it up again, and many other ſorts of Riches, which he dare not make uſe of, either for his own Relief, or the Relief of the Poor.—Secondly, <hi>That ſome men enjoy many things which they do not poſſeſs.</hi> He that is ſo refin'd and ſpiritualiz'd, as to view all things in God, and to take notice of the Goodneſs, Sweetneſs, and Bounty of God in the whole Creation,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98767:36"/> and has ſuch an Intereſt in Chriſt Jeſus, and in the Love of GOD, as to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him to ſay, All things are mine; and ſo much Charity, as to delight in the Good of his Neighbour as his own, enjoys even the very Poſſeſſions of other men, and all that is ſweet and excellent in them, as truly, and more purely, than if they were his own. As the little Bee, that flies from Flower to Flower in any man's Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den whatſoever, and ſucks out the ſweetneſs thereof, ſo does the Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Soul extract true ſweetneſs out of all the Works of God, though they be the Poſſeſſions of other men, and by this rare Art makes them his own, at leaſt takes more Pleaſure in them than the Owner.</p>
            <p>But this is a Digreſſion not here to be handled, and perhaps too curious to be well underſtood; to return therefore,</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:98767:37"/>
            <p> The <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure</hi> that is taken in Worldly Poſſeſſions is but fanciful and imaginary; the Fancy is tickled, but the higher Powers of the Soul are not really ſatisfied, nor indeed pleaſed. As the Sports and Delights of Children are inferiour to the Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Satisfactions of grown Men; and as the Laughter of Fools differs from the Pleaſure and Contentment of Princes; as the crackling of Thorns under a Pot differs from a Fire made of a good ſubſtantial pile of Coals; as the uncertain, unſteddy, and ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky light of green Wood differs from the ſtrong, ſteddy, and pure flame of the dry Tree; ſo much do the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhes, Pleaſures, and Delights which men have and find in ſublunary Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, fall ſhort of the true, pure, perfect Satisfactions and Raviſhments which are the Entertainment of the other World. <hi>As the crackling of thorns</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:98767:37"/> 
               <hi>under a pot, ſo is the laughter of a fool: this alſo is vanity, Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 6. Yea, <hi>Solomon</hi> was no Fool, yet he ſaid in his Heart, <hi>Go to now, I will prove thee with mirth, therefore enjoy pleaſure;</hi> and <hi>behold, this alſo is vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Eccleſ.</hi> 2. 1. In the midſt of this fanciful Laughter the Heart is often ſad, ſorrowful, pincht, and pin'd; and generally the occaſion of our ſenſual Merriment, if it were well conſider'd, deſerves indeed to be the cauſe of ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Grief and Sorrow.</p>
            <p>And this imaginary kind of Pleaſure and Delight that we take in Earthly Poſſeſſions, is flitting and evanid too. The Pleaſure that the greateſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualiſt in the World takes in his Meat or Drink, or any other ſenſual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, laſts no longer than whilſt the Neceſſitys of Nature are in ſupplying, or the Appetites are grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying. When the Appetites and Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98767:38"/> of Nature are once gratified, then farewel all Pleaſure, no more Delight, no more Reliſh remains: And till theſe Appetites and Cravings are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, all ſenſual Pleaſure and Delight is wanting; and, Who would deſire to be hungry on purpoſe, only that he might have the pleaſure of eating? <hi>Surely every man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi> As to what he poſſeſſeth, and as to the Delight he takes in thoſe Poſſeſſions, they <hi>periſh with the uſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the third Head, <hi>Every man walketh in a vain ſhew,</hi> as to what he <hi>does</hi> or <hi>undertakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under this Head I comprehend all humane Plots, Projects, and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, as to all which one may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, <hi>Man walketh in a vain ſhew.</hi> There are many Devices in the Heart of Man, which ought not to be there,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98767:38"/> and there are many there that never proſper, many that do take effect, and it had been better they had been abortive: And after all, in a ſhort time, this plotting Head is laid in the Duſt, and all Man's Thoughts do pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with him.</p>
            <p>There are many proud, revengeful, ambitious, covetous Devices in the Heart of Man, which ought not to be there. <hi>I am reſolved what to do,</hi> ſays the Rich man in the Goſpel, <hi>I will pull down my barns, and build bigger; and I will ſay to my ſoul, Soul, thou haſt much goods laid up for many years, take thy eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry, Luke</hi> 12. 18. <hi>q. d.</hi> I am reſolved now to lead a merry Life for many years. What a vain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, what an infirm Device this was, the next words declare; <hi>Thou fool, this night thy ſoul ſhall be required of thee, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore we read of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98767:39"/> 
               <hi>an heart that deviſeth wicked imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Prov.</hi> 6. 18. and of the Heathens, that were <hi>vain in their imaginations, Rom.</hi> 1. 21. and of imagining <hi>a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Device, Pſal.</hi> 21. 11. Such a miſchievous Device was that of <hi>Eſau</hi> againſt his Brother <hi>Jacob, The days of mourning for my Father are at hand; then will I kill my Brother Jacob, Gen.</hi> 26. 41.</p>
            <p>Again, There are many Projects and Devices in the Heart of Man, which never proſper; according to that of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 19. 21. <hi>There are many devices in a man's heart, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs the counſel of the Lord that ſhall ſtand. Balaam</hi> plotted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, and uſed all Charms imaginable againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to curſe and deſtroy them, and yet it came to this at laſt, <hi>Surely there is no enchantment againſt Jacob, nor divination againſt Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 23. 23. Nay, honeſt Plots,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98767:39"/> and innocent Contrivances, which men, yea, good men, employ their Heads and Hearts about, often prove abortive; yea, when they are, as one may ſay, come to the birth, there does not prove to be Strength enough to bring forth. <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſet his Heart upon making <hi>David</hi> King, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed himſelf a great Contentment in it, becauſe he loved him, and knew that he was wonderfully and paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately beloved of him; <hi>Thou ſhalt be King, and I ſhall be next unto thee,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 17. A very fair and probable Plot, a very likely Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture; but alas, it miſcarried: <hi>David</hi> indeed liv'd to be King, but <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> never liv'd to ſee it. Let a Project be ſpun as fine as a Spider's Web, a little Accident, ſome ſmall Circumſtance no bigger than a Bee may break it.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:98767:40"/>
            <p> Again, There are many Projects and Devices in the Hearts of the Sons of men, that do take effect, and it had been much better they had been abortive, and theſe purpoſes fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Who knoweth,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon, what is good for man in this life, all the days of his vain life, which he ſpendeth as a ſhadow, Eccleſ.</hi> 6. 12? Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? Indeed many men have thought they have known, but they have been miſerably miſtaken. It had been a thouſand times better for many men to have had their Plots and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances fruſtrated and diſappointed, than gratified or perform'd. <hi>Amnon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with his Couſin <hi>Jonadab,</hi> and ſubtilly contrived to fulfill his ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous Luſt upon his Siſter <hi>Tamar; And Jonadab,</hi> ſays the Text, <hi>was a very ſubtile man,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. but <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadab</hi> had better have been a Fool, than to have given ſuch Counſel; and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98767:40"/> 
               <hi>Amnon</hi> was a Fool for following it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt be as one of the fools in Iſrael.</hi> And indeed by this ſubtile Plot he loſt not only his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, but his Life too, <hi>ver.</hi> 28, 29. <hi>Haman</hi> the <hi>Agagite</hi> plotted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived cunningly againſt <hi>Mordecai,</hi> by obtaining a Decree from the King for the murdering of a whole Nation at once, for ſo he knew that <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai</hi> could not eſcape. Well, he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the Decree, and thought to glut his Eyes with their Blood, little thinking that the Queen herſelf was a Jew, and that unhappy Miſtake brought him to the Gallows. What Contrivances and Plottings are to be found every where, for the procuring of Places, the getting of rich Matches, the eſtabliſhing of Trade, the encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Riches, which after a ſhort time the Projectors wiſh had rather been fruſtrated and diſappointed than accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:98767:41"/>
            <p> And laſtly, After all, vain Man lays his plotting Head in the Duſt, and then, at leaſt then, <hi>all his thoughts periſh, Pſal.</hi> 146. 4. His Breath goeth forth, he returneth to his Earth, in that very day his Thoughts periſh. <hi>Sennacherib</hi> plots againſt poor helpleſs <hi>Judah,</hi> and makes himſelf ſure of her; <hi>With the multitude of my chariots I am come up to the height of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, to the ſides of Lebanon, and will cut down the tall Cedar trees thereof; and I will enter into the lodgings of his borders, and into the Foreſt of his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19. 23. Well, the next News is, <hi>It came to paſs that night, that the Angel of the Lord went out and ſmote in the camp of the Aſſyrians an hundred fourſcore and five thouſand, ver.</hi> 35. The King himſelf returned (with ſhame enough you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) and whilſt he was at his Idol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, his Sons ſmote him with the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98767:41"/> Sword; <hi>ver.</hi> 37. <hi>Thou fool, this night ſhall thy ſoul be required of thee, and then, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to conſider Man as to what he <hi>enterprizes</hi> and <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes,</hi> and to ſhew, that therein alſo he walketh in a <hi>vain ſhew. Solomon</hi> was a man of the greateſt Undertakings that the Sun ever ſaw: You may ſee an Epitome of his Labours and Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, and the many things that he ſet his Hand unto, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2. and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, he turned himſelf, and looked on all the Works that his Hand had wrought, and on the Labour that he had laboured to do, and behold, all was <hi>Vanity,</hi> and there was <hi>no profit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun, ver.</hi> 11. As to that which Man undertakes, <hi>he diſquiets himſelf in vain,</hi> ſays the Pſalmiſt here in the Text; the Verb is of the plural number in the Hebrew, becauſe of the Collective <hi>Iſh,</hi> or <hi>every man,</hi> going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98767:42"/> and is tranſlated <hi>tumultuantur, turbantur, perſtrepunt:</hi> They make a great deal of buſtle and clutter, and diſquiet themſelves, and indeed they diſquiet the neighbouring World round about them, as <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great did of old, and <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth does at this day, and all in vain. <hi>Surely every man walketh in a vain ſhew, they diſquiet themſelves in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would be endleſs to run through all the Actions, Undertakings, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes of men in the World in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. In general, there is a great deal of buſtle, commotion, diſturbance, diſtraction, made by this ſilly <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal</hi> called Man, upon the Stage of this World, and all to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>One arms himſelf and all his Vaſſals cap-a-pee, and goes out into the Field, to amaze and affright the impotent
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98767:42"/> and on-looking World, he wins Towns and Countries, he adds Kingdom to Kingdom, enlarges his Dominions, ſpreads his Language, advances his Name, erects Statues and Trophies, and yet this great Undertaker obtains no real Intereſt, Love, or Honour in the Hearts of his fellow-Creatures, he does not approve himſelf to God, he has no Favour from his holy Angels; His exalted Name will ſoon be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, his ſtately Trophies in a ſhort time demoliſh'd, and himſelf to the end of the World confin'd to a few feet of Earth; and after all, the great <hi>Hero</hi> ſhall be judg'd as another man, as the meaneſt <hi>private Centi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another is continually contriving for his Appetite, how to gratifie that; he ſearches the Air, the Earth, the Seas; he ranſacks the World for Meat for his Belly, or Sawce for his Meat,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98767:43"/> or curious Cookery for both. Theſe Dainties are hard and coſtly to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; when they are gotten, they gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie but for a Meal, they periſh with the uſing, and loſe all their ſweetneſs, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the cravings of this ſilly whining Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite are once gratified. After theſe, freſh Entertainments muſt be ſought out, and after thoſe ſtill new ones, or elſe the childiſh whimpering Appetite cannot be quieted: In all which much Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is ſpent, many Hands employed, much of Man's vain ſhort life waſted, and great Eſtates many times exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, many men feeding their Capons with Currans ſo long, till themſelves have not a Capon nor ſo much as a Hen to feed upon. In the mean time the Stomach is rather cloy'd than truly gratified, and the Conſtitution rather ſurfeited and depraved, than nouriſhed or ſtrengthened; and after all, that heavy Doom of the Apoſtle takes place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>Meats for</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:98767:43"/> 
               <hi>the belly, and the belly for meats, but God ſhall deſtroy both it and them.</hi> And the Worms will make no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, nor find no difference between their Carcaſſes and the Fleſh of meaner Mortals.</p>
            <p>Another runs up and down the World, catching here and there, goes into this City, and that Country and Kingdom, to buy and ſell, and traffick, and get Gain; where there is any Market, or Fair, or concourſe of People for <hi>Trade,</hi> there is he. His whole Enquiry is, <hi>Who will ſhew us any Good?</hi> and his whole buſineſs to acquire it. The whole deſign and buſineſs of his vain and vexatious Life is to gather Riches, and yet (ſee how he <hi>walks in a vain ſhew!)</hi> perhaps he can no more catch theſe Riches than a man can catch a Shadow; or if he do catch them, they are but a Shadow ſtill: And to whom he ſhall leave them he cannot tell.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98767:44"/> Perhaps (I ſay) he can no more catch them than a Man can catch a Shadow. Riches in this reſpect are much a-kin to Honour, of which it uſes to be ſaid, <hi>Sequentem fugit fugien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſequitur;</hi> it flees him that follows it, and follows him that flees from it. They look for Riches; they look for much, but lo, it comes to little; and if they bring it home, the Providence of GOD, the Blaſt of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bloweth upon it! <hi>Haggai</hi> 1. 9. Or, as the ſame Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>They ſow much and bring in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, eat and have not enough, cloth them, but there is none warm, earn wages, and put it into a bag with holes. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> a plodding Mammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, left no Stone unturn'd, no way uneſſay'd to multiply his Flocks, and grow very pecoroſe; he changed his Servants Wages ten times; he requir'd the ſtoln and the torn at the Hands of his Shepherd; but Heaven found out a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98767:44"/> way to fruſtrate him, and after all, his Shepherd died as rich as he.</p>
            <p>Or if he do catch them, they are but a ſhadow ſtill, no ſubſtance, weight, or ſolid worth in them, no Virtue to fill the Soul, to ſatisfie the Deſires, to ſtill the Cravings, or allay the raging Appetites of a Worldly Mind. It is with vain Man in this reſpect, as the Prophet elegantly expreſſes it, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9. 20. <hi>He ſnatcheth on the right hand, and yet is hungry; he eats on the left hand, and is not ſatisfied.</hi> The Deſires and Cravings of Minds and Spirits can be no more ſatisfied with Gold and Silver, than the Hungerings of the Body can be allay'd with Words, or ſatisfied with Notions and Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. <hi>Solomon,</hi> that had all things, was ſatisfied with nothing, but ſtill cries out, <hi>All is vanity;</hi> and <hi>there is no profit under the ſun. He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſilver, ſhall not be ſatisfied with</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:98767:45"/> 
               <hi>ſilver, nor he that loveth abundance with encreaſe, Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 10. Nay, it is a thouſand to one but Vexation is added to the Vanity. Worldly Wealth does only not ſatisfie, but oftentimes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſteth the Owner, tempts him to Pride, Security, Forgetfulneſs of God, and diſdaining of Men; expoſes him to Envy, and that lays him open to Thieves, and abundance of Snares and Dangers, makes him lead an unquiet life, anxious days, and wakeful nights, whilſt he is ſollicitous how to keep them whilſt he lives, and how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them when he dyes: And it's ten to one, he is as much hated or laugh'd at when he is dead, as he was envied whilſt he lived; which brings me to the third thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom he ſhall leave them he cannot tell.</hi> If he have no Child of his own Body begotten, he is all his Life time ſollicited by his own, or it
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98767:45"/> may be his Wives Relations, and at his Death he is ſollicitous how to diſtribute his Wealth; if he give all to one, the reſt will judge him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, and be ready to curſe his Aſhes; if he diſtribute it amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, it ſpoils the great deſign of making one only very great and rich, and the pretty Plot of keeping up the Name and Grandeur of a Family. If he have an Heir of his own Body to tranſmit his Wealth to; then if it be a Daughter, he fears her great Portion will betray her to ſome idle ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering Gentleman or other, that will firſt impoveriſh her, and then hate her; firſt get rid of what ſhe has, and then ſeek to be rid of her too. If it be a Son, ſtill (alas!) who knows whether he ſhall be a Wiſe man or a Fool, whether he will be induſtrious or profuſe? This fretted King <hi>Solomon</hi> whilſt he was alive, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2. 18, 19. <hi>I muſt leave it unto</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:98767:46"/> 
               <hi>the man that ſhall be after me; and who knoweth whether he ſhall be a wiſe man or a fool?</hi> And indeed (as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks) the thing that he feared came upon him; for his Son and Heir <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> fooliſhly forſook the Counſel of the grave Senators, and follow'd the raſh Advice of his giddy beardleſs Courtiers, and in one day loſt ten parts in twelve of that great Eſtate which his Grandfather with ſo much Hazard and Courage had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd, and his Father with ſo much Care and Prudence had ſo long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd. Was not this a fooliſh Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Son, who at one ſitting rent off ten parts in twelve of a Kingdom, which his Father had kept together forty years? And does not this ſort of men walk in a vain ſhew?</p>
            <p>Another plods day and night, ſpends his Time and Strength in endleſs En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries after Knowledge, which Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98767:46"/> are ſometimes bootleſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly painful, and always imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p>They are ſometimes <hi>bootleſs;</hi> for, how often do poor Mortals ſearch for the hidden Treaſures of the knowledge of many things both in Nature and Divinity, which they find out even as they find out the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher's Stone, ſought by many, but found by none; who whilſt they ſeek an Art to turn all things into Gold, only find a way to turn all their own Gold into nothing. The Apoſtle, I remember, ſpeaks it to the reproach of ſome ſilly Women, that were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies learning, and never yet were able to come to the knowledge of the Truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 7. I believe the Character may as well be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd to fooliſh and vain men, as to ſilly Women; for how many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious men are to be found in the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98767:47"/> World, who by the moſt diligent ſearch could never arrive at the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of many things which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd; and becauſe God did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal it to them, reſolv'd to conſult the Devil, and make him their Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligencer and Interpreter? Certainly the Thirſt after Knowledge is no leſs vehement than after Silver and Gold: I doubt not, but that many curious, inquiſitive, and fine Minds are as ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and vehement in this Caſe, as the Merchant that we read of in the Parable, who ſold all his Poſſeſſions to buy the Field in which was the Pearl of great price: As appears by the Saying of a young Nobleman of this Kingdom (not then Two and Twenty years old) in a Book entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Seraphick Love,</hi> that he would gladly exchange all the Honour and Eſtate that he had in this World, for the knowledge of Natural things, and their Cauſes.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:98767:47"/>
            <p> Theſe Enquiries after Knowledge are commonly <hi>painful;</hi> to which I may add <hi>coſtly.</hi> The knowledge of things indeed by Inſpiration, may ſeem to be eaſie, (and yet the inſpired Prieſts and Prieſteſſes of the Heathen gods labour'd under great Diſtreſs and Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, whilſt they were <hi>pleni deo,</hi> as they call'd it, and in plain Engliſh, <hi>beſides themſelves).</hi> This Knowledge (I ſay) by Inſpiration, may ſeem to be eaſie; but yet <hi>Solomon,</hi> who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was alſo ſometimes (at leaſt) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd, tells us, That <hi>much ſtudy is a wearineſs of the fleſh, Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 12. And the expence of the Animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and the fatigue of the Brain, is confeſt by all men skilful in human Bodies, to be greater than the travel of the Feet, or the labour of the Hands. To ſpeak nothing of the coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of enquiring after Knowledge, in ſome reſpects, (though the charge
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98767:48"/> of Education, Books, and Travels might be reaſonably ſuggeſted) the moſt ſtudious and inquiſitive men do find to their Coſt and Vexation of Mind, many things, which they may wiſh they had been ignorant of, and by the pretence of knowing many things, come to this miſerable paſs, to be forc'd to confeſs their own Ignorance, and to acknowledge, that they know nothing. But of all the Painfulneſs and Vexation which belongs to the Enquiries after Knowledge, nothing ſeems to me to be a greater, than the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreſolvedneſs</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſatisfiedneſs</hi> of mens Minds, after they have made all theſe Enquiries. After all, to heſitate and be doubtful, and to cry out in the anguiſh of ones Mind with <hi>Solomon, Who knows,</hi> and <hi>who can tell?</hi> Lord, what a Diſeaſe is this in the human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and what a ſtate of Vanity does it argue! but this I paſs by, as having ſpoken ſomething of it before.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:98767:48"/>
            <p> Laſtly, This Knowledge we get by all our Enquiries is very <hi>poor, mean,</hi> and <hi>imperfect,</hi> in compariſon of the Viſions and Intuitions of the other World, when we ſhall ſee as we are ſeen, and know as we are known, feaſt upon Truth itſelf, and behold all things in God, and him in the pure Rays of his own Divinity. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> knew much, but he did not know the whole, and that which he did know he knew but in part, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 9, 10. <hi>We know in part, but when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall be done away.</hi> But this alſo I toucht upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay of vain Man? It is impoſſible to enumerate his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues and Vanities. In ſhort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:98767:49"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Does he work?</hi> Then he wearies himſelf, and exhauſts his Strength. <hi>Does he play?</hi> Then he forgets him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and emaſculates his Spirits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Does he Trade by Land?</hi> Then he is either tempted to cheat, or liable to be cheated, either to get another mans unduly, or to have his own got from him deceitfully.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Does he Traffick by Sea?</hi> He may indeed ſee the Wonders of the Lord in the Deep, but no greater Wonder, than that he himſelf is not there. Who but vain Man would expoſe his Life to ſo eminent Dangers, for things not neceſſary to Life, yea, ſome that are more hurtful than uſeful; and all the Sweets of his Family and Country for a few foreign Spices?</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:98767:49"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Does he go into Wars?</hi> He lies at the Mercy of every random bit of Lead, ſhot by a Fool, or a Child, or a Mad-man: If he conquer and kill, here is no cauſe of glorying, one would think, to have ſent his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Body to the Grave, and, it may be, his Soul to Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Does he purchaſe?</hi> He is either miſtaken in the Title, abus'd by the Law, envy'd or hated by his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. However, would he but be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and ſtay a while, he ſhould have Earth enough to ſerve his turn, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Coſt or Charge at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Does he marry?</hi> He does certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall into Incumbrances. <hi>Does he vow a ſingle life?</hi> He does as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall into Snares. If he marry, he is fain to endure the <hi>Yoke;</hi> if he do not, he has much ado to endure to be <hi>curb'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:98767:50"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Does he ſtudy Day and Night?</hi> Poor man! with a great deal of Pain and Wearineſs he comes to underſtand, that all things are Uncertainty and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, a thing that one had better ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have known. And after all, <hi>How dyeth the wiſe man? even as the fool dyeth, Eccleſ.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Does he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrate differences, and make peace? bleſſed is he,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: But for all that, he ſhall be ſure to meet with many a Curſe. To go about to pleaſe both Parties, is as if a man ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to ſerve two Maſters; which no body can well do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Does he court the Favour of great men by Fawning and Flattery?</hi> It is a great Slavery to an ingenuous and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Mind; the Favour of wiſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will not be ſo gotten: And if they be fooliſh and inconſtant, it will be ſoon loſt.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:98767:50"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Is he active, and brisk, and a lover of buſineſs?</hi> He diſquiets himſelf; yea, active Tempers, that cannot ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage their own Metal, many times diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet the World about them. He that does much, will certainly ſometimes do amiſs; if he ſhould do all things well, he will yet be accounted a Buſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is he idle, careleſs, and unconcern'd?</hi> He is then a ſelfiſh Sot, an unprofitable Member of the Univerſe. He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards nothing, does not himſelf deſerve to be regarded.</p>
            <p>In a word, Caſt your Eyes over the World, and behold the Diſeaſes and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes of ſome, and what will you call it but an <hi>Hoſpital?</hi> Behold the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions and Diſorders of all the reſt in one kind or other, and what will you call it but a <hi>Bethlehem?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:98767:51"/>
            <p> And ſo I come, in the laſt place, briefly to conſider Man in the higheſt acts of Human Life, <hi>viz.</hi> his <hi>religious acts,</hi> and to ſhew, that even in them alſo he walketh in a vain ſhew; or, to give it you in the Pſalmiſt's words elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>Every man at his beſt eſtate is altogether vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, theſe <hi>Religious</hi> acts are either outward or inward. As to <hi>outward</hi> acts; Men do not only work and trade, but even pray and come to Church in a vain ſhew. Not only Markets and Fairs, but even religious Aſſemblies and Congregations are a ſhew too, which men walk in, whilſt they pretend to walk with God. Thoſe make a great noiſe in the Ears of Men, and theſe are little better than a noiſe in the Ears of Heaven. Who can deny, but that the Worſhip of the Prophane is a vain ſhew, who to day ſwear by the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98767:51"/> Name of God, and to morrow call upon the Name of God; to day eat unto Gluttony, and drink unto Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, to morrow eat the Fleſh and drink the Blood of the Son of God; to day pray to God to damn them, and to morrow pray him to ſave them; to day behave themſelves ſo reverently, as if God were in the Head, and to morrow live as if there were no God in Heaven? Who can imagine but GOD and Men too muſt loath ſuch impious Vanity as this is? Who can deny, but that the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous and Superſtitious Worſhippers walk in a vain ſhew, who worſhip ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they know not what, or they care not how, offering up ſtrange Fire to God, and indeed affronting him, whilſt they pretend to adore him? Who can deny, but that the Worldling, who has ſet up the World in his Heart for his Idol, walks in a vain ſhew, who ſits before God as an attentive Hearer of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98767:52"/> his Word, and makes much love to him with his Lips, when his Heart is far from him, and runs after his Covetouſneſs? Who can deny, but the Hypocrite walks in a vain ſhew, who comes with his <hi>God I thank thee,</hi> in his Mouth, when he has no love for him in his Heart, who confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Sins which he has no mind to part with; who begs the Grace which he has no mind to receive, who ſeems to condemn and humble himſelf before God, in the mean time is great in his own Eyes, and ceaſes not upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to magnifie and applaud him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before men.</p>
            <p>But ſome one will ſay, All men are not prophane, worldly, idolatrous, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical, there are ſome ſubſtantial Worſhippers, that worſhip the Father <hi>in Spirit and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:98767:52"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true indeed, <hi>The father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him, Joh.</hi> 4. 23. but I doubt he <hi>findeth</hi> few; for (not to ſtrain the Apoſtle's words to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt and moſt uncharitable ſence, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 19. <hi>Totus mundus poſitus eſt in maligno)</hi> though <hi>Prophaneneſs</hi> may be eaſily diſcerned, yet ſure I am, predominant <hi>Worldlineſs</hi> and <hi>Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> are in many Hearts, where they are not diſcover'd; nay, it is to be feared, the falſe Heart itſelf will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of them. And as for <hi>Idolatry,</hi> though the foreign Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches do all put it off from themſelves, to the Heathen and Antichriſtian Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet I fear, concerning ſome of them, one may take up <hi>Samuel</hi>'s words to <hi>Saul, If ye have indeed deſtroyed Idolatry utterly, what<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> means this bleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſheep, and lowing of the oxen which I hear?</hi> If any one ſhould an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as <hi>Saul</hi> did, we have reſerved theſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98767:53"/> innocent, ſafe, and ſignificant Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, to ſacrifice to the Lord, to adorn and grace the Worſhip of God; it will perhaps be replied, as <hi>Samuel</hi> replies, <hi>Obedience is better than Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;</hi> or, as another Prophet expreſſes it, <hi>Quis ne quiſivit hoec?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer further, What man is there upon Earth, in whom theſe Sins are not found in ſome degree or other? And ſo far as they are found, they do pollute the Worſhip, and ſubject it to the denomination of Vanity.</p>
            <p>But I anſwer, <hi>thirdly,</hi> That the word <hi>Tſelem</hi> in the Text does not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a <hi>vain ſhew</hi> properly, but a ſhew, a reſemblance, a repreſentation, or image, in oppoſition to ſubſtantial; as the Picture which we ſee in a Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glaſs is the repreſentation or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the Face that looks into it. And ſo every man, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98767:53"/> may be ſaid to walk <hi>betſelem in imagine,</hi> in a ſhew, as to his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acts; which I ſhall further explain under the next Head, <hi>viz.</hi> his inward religious acts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>internal</hi> actings of Grace are but a ſhew, a reſemblance of ſome ſuch thing, in compariſon of what they were in Man <hi>innocent,</hi> or ſhall be in Man <hi>glorified.</hi> The inward pious acts of our Minds do make us approach the neareſt to Subſtance of any thing that we have or do: For <hi>as a man thinketh in his heart,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, ſo is he.</hi> If any thing will denominate a man a ſubſtantial Chriſtian, it is theſe inward Acts of the Mind, the Acts of Faith, Hope, and Love, the Acts of Self-denial and Contempt of the World, and of the whole Creation in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Creator: And yet even theſe are but a ſhew, a reſemblance of ſomething rather than any thing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:98767:54"/>
            <p> The <hi>Love</hi> that the moſt affectionate, devout, and refined Soul exerciſes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards GOD in this mixt ſtate, is but a ſhadow, a reſemblance of Love, in compariſon of the Ardours of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World. <hi>I love thee,</hi> ſaid <hi>Peter, I love thee,</hi> yea, <hi>Lord thou knoweſt that I love thee, John</hi> 21. 15, 16, 17. Poor <hi>Peter!</hi> I believe in a degree he did love him; yet I believe he was grieved that he could love him no better. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy ſoul, with all thy mind, with all thy ſtrength, Mark</hi> 12. 30. This is the firſt and great Commandment; a great one in deed! <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; And who is able to perform it? How many <hi>Alls</hi> are here? <hi>All</hi> and <hi>All,</hi> and <hi>All</hi> and <hi>All.</hi> Lord, what mortal man can with any Modeſty pretend to ſuch a generous Love as this is? Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that has his Senſes exerciſed,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98767:54"/> to diſcern between Good and Evil, will confeſs that this Command is juſt, equal, and reaſonable, yea, and very pleaſant too, (for what is, what can be ſweeter than a Life of Love?) But yet the moſt devout, the moſt amorous and ardent Soul that this day inhabits a mortal Body, muſt needs confeſs his Straitneſs, and bewail his Unaffectionateneſs; and though he may ſeem to be drench'd in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paſſion, yet has cauſe to pray, Lord, ſhed abroad the Love of God in me. <hi>Perfect love</hi> (ſays the loving and beloved Apoſtle) <hi>caſts out fear,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 18. Alas! Where is this perfect Love then? for Fear, yea, ſome degree of ſlaviſh Fear, is found in every Heart of Man; yea, though he love GOD ſincerely and ardent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too, yet he is apt to fear he does not love him enough: The hotteſt of our Love is cold, the ſtrongeſt is weak and faint, in compariſon of what
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98767:55"/> 
               <hi>Adam</hi>'s once was, and <hi>Abraham</hi>'s now is. We call it Love indeed, but it is rather Liking than Love, rather han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering than either. It is but a going Fire, a Glow-worm, at beſt but a Blaze or a Blazing-Star, in compariſon of the Fervors, the Delights, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placencies of the Spirits of <hi>Juſt men made perfect.</hi> The greateſt zeal of mortal Man for GOD, (which yet is the Flower of Love) is in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the angelical Ferver, but as a Fire painted upon the Wall, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of that which burneth upon the Hearth. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was as zealous for his Lord, and did and ſuffer'd as much for him as any of his Diſciples whatſoever, ſo that in nothing was he behind the chiefeſt Apoſtles; yet he eſteemed himſelf as <hi>nothing,</hi> which is not ſo much as a <hi>ſhew,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 11.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:98767:55"/>
            <p> How weak and tottering is the <hi>Truſt</hi> and Confidence in GOD, which the moſt ſteddy Soul can pretend to in this World, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the unmixt and unſhaken Affiance in him, which conſtitutes the Joy and Security of the other World? The three unmartyr'd Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. are renowned for their Faith and firm Dependance upon their GOD, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>He will deliver us out of thy hands, O King.</hi> This was their Confidence in GOD; but it had its <hi>If</hi> for all that, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>But if not, be it known to thee, O King, &amp;c.</hi> But the Affiances and Aſſurances of the other World are above all <hi>Buts</hi> and <hi>Ifs:</hi> The ſtouteſt of our Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence here, is but a ſhadow of that Confidence, which ſhall have no <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of turning.</hi> What fear of miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying can there poſſibly be to him, who perpetually walks in the light of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98767:56"/> God's Countenance? what Danger, what Suſpicion can there be of being pluckt from thence, to a Soul folded in the Arms, and wrapt up in the Boſom of the Almighty?</p>
            <p>And what is our <hi>Hope</hi> in this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſtate? A poor languid thing, a faint Velerity, a dull yawning, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a greedy gaſping, a lifeleſs ſtretching forth the Hands towards, rather than an eager laying hold upon Eternal Life. It ought to be an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and vehement Longing, and alas! it ſcarce amounts to a ſincere Deſire or Expectation.</p>
            <p>And what are our Acts of <hi>Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial,</hi> in compariſon of the exinani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the glorified Saints, who caſt down their Crowns before the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. 10.—What is our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World,</hi> in compariſon of that Diſdain with which refined and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98767:56"/> glorified Souls behold all earthly Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, eying and enjoying all things in GOD alone? Alas! what mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal man can <hi>oculo irritorto ſpectare acervos,</hi> with an Eye altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dazzled, or with a Heart altogether unaffected and diſengaged, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the Bravery and Grandeur, the precious and gliſtering Poſſeſſions of this World, (whether his own or other mens) perfectly free from Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I mean, who can do it, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dote nor envy? But they that are got above the Sun, and look down with the Eyes of Angels, do ſee all things under the Sun to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Vanity, a ſore Vexation and Labour, and that there is no Profit in them, as <hi>Solomon</hi> expreſſes it.</p>
            <p>How pinch'd and narrow are the moſt enlarged and capacious Souls upon Earth in their <hi>Thanks</hi> and <hi>Praiſes</hi> to the Almighty Goodneſs, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98767:57"/> of the noble Raptures and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhments of glorified Spirits, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſe to chant forth the Praiſes of God, ſinging the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>Bleſſing and honour, and glory, and power be unto him that ſitteth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the throne, Rev.</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Bleſſing, and glory, and wiſdom, and thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and honour, and power, and might be unto our God for ever and ever, Rev.</hi> 7. 12.</p>
            <p>In a word, How poor and inſipid, how dull and ſtagnant are the <hi>Joys</hi> and <hi>Delights</hi> of the beſt aſſured and moſt ſatisfied Souls upon Earth, in compariſon of the pure, ſtrong, active, and raviſhing Complacencies which are the Portion of the Spirits of juſt men made perfect; when all their Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are filled up to the very brim of their reſpective Capacities, with the Communications of Divine Grace, Light, Life, and Love, and the bleſſed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98767:57"/> creature is made all that which the ever bleſſed Creator is, ſo far as his finite and limitted nature will permit. How mean is the Satisfaction that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Souls do reap, who ſit down by the Streams, and drink a little to allay their Thirſt, in compariſon of the Solaces of glorified Souls, who are always in an extaſie of freſh and unfading Joys, who are ſtill drenching themſelves in Fulneſs of Joy, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing themſelves in Rivers of Pleaſure, which are at God's right hand for evermore. It was properly ſaid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the good and faithful Servant, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 21. <hi>Enter thou into the joy of thy Lord,</hi> becauſe it was impoſſible that the infinite Joy of his Lord ſhould enter into him.</p>
            <p>But here ſome one will be apt to cry out with the paſſionate Pſalmiſt, complaining of his own and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Afflictions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 47. <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:98767:58"/> 
               <hi>wherefore haſt thou made all men in vain?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, GOD made Man upright, holy, bleſſed, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, but Sin hath brought Vanity upon Mankind; yea, the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is thereby ſubjected to Vanity. Man, in departing from his GOD, who is Life and Subſtance, is become vain, and whatever he is, has, or does, is but imperfect, is but a ſhew. But yet GOD has not made all Men in vain neither, becauſe he has yet or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd for all believing Souls a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial and durable ſtate of Happineſs; ſo that though they be mean and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect in this World, they ſhall be perfect and compleat in another.</p>
            <p>Let us rather cry out with the ſame Pſalmiſt, when he was in a more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene and undiſturbed Temper, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. 4. <hi>Lord, what is man, that thou art</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:98767:58"/> 
               <hi>mindful of him, or the Son of man, that thou viſiteſt him?</hi> What is poor Man, whom his Sin and Apoſtaſie has made ſo vain and deſpicable, that thou after all this ſhouldſt think Thoughts of Love towards him, and prepare ſuch excellent Honour and Happineſs for him? How great cauſe have all the poor crippled Souls of Men to admire the infinite Bounty of the Great King, and to cry out with lame <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 28. we were all but as dead Souls before God, yet has He ſet us amongſt the Angels of Heaven, and will entertain us with them that eat at his own Table.</p>
            <p>And this indeed might ſerve for one uſe that I would make of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but this is not all; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:98767:59"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This may ſerve to humble the Children of Men, to pull down their proud Creſts, and to reduce them to a ſober Temper. This is one of the moſt notorious and odious Vanities of vain Man, that he does think highly of himſelf, and magnifies himſelf in his own Eyes, and is ambitious to be Great in the Eyes of other men. There is nothing more miſerable than the Devils, and yet nothing prouder than they. Even <hi>Simon Magus</hi> himſelf, the Sorcerer, that <hi>Child of the Devil,</hi> was deſirous to be accounted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſome great one</hi> amongſt his Neighbors. It is a common and true Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that by how much the leſs worth any man has, the more he is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his own Worthineſs, and ſeeks to put off himſelf in the eſtimation of the World: Whereas the Wiſe and the Good, <hi>ſuâ ſe virtute involvunt,</hi> are ſatisfied in and from themſelves, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98767:59"/> are ſufficiently defended by a conciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their own Worth and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and goodneſs of their Cauſe, and had rather be accounted to have nothing to ſay, than to anſwer Fools according to their Folly; had rather forſeit their Reputation than their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion. Now, what can be thought of more effectual for the correcting the Inſolence of vain Man, than to be throughly convinc'd of his own Vanity? If the Bubble could be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded it was but a Bubble, ſurely it would ſwell no more. If Man could be perſwaded, that he was <hi>a Worm, and no Man,</hi> he would be content with a humble crawling upon the Earth, and not magnifie himſelf, as if he were not a creeping thing. If any thing in the World can enoble Man, and make him ſomething, it is Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; and if any thing in the World can humble him, it muſt be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his own Vanity and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingneſs.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:98767:60"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was juſtly eſteemed by the wiſe Greeks as a Voice from Heaven, as an Oracle of God, <hi>è coelo deſcendit;</hi> and I think the Chriſtian Divinity acknowledges the ſame. When the noble Souls of men do conſider their own original, how pure and excellent it was, how they are now ſunk into Priſons of Fleſh, and inverſt in Sence and Senſuality, how dark they are in their Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, how unſteddy in their Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, how uncertain in their Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, how irregular in their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how boiſterous and unreaſonable in their Paſſions, how eaſily carried away to Vice, how imperfect in Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, how weak, diſtempered, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed in Body, how diſappointed in Relations, how vex'd, tir'd, deceiv'd, or oppreſt in their Eſtates, how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex'd in this World, and how doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of a better; in a word, what a bun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle of Vanity Mankind is become, how
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:98767:60"/> can it be, but that it muſt needs make him ſober and humble, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contribute ſomething to the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him to his primitive Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; <hi>Nam quò minus ſibi arrogat homo, eò evadit clarior &amp; nobilior;</hi> The leſs Man arrogates to himſelf, the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent he is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let this Doctrine of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Vanity affect our Hearts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionately towards the miſerable apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Sons of Men. Of all Sights in this World, this is the ſaddeſt, and moſt to be lamented; Nations unhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, Kingdoms weltering in Blood, the moſt deviliſh Plots, the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Wars, the moſt barbarous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions that ever the Eye of a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator beheld, or the Pen of an Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian recorded, if they were all regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, would not make up ſuch a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Volume, as the third Chapter of <hi>Geneſis</hi> alone does. We pitty the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98767:61"/> Wounded when we ſee their Wounds bleeding, and their Limbs broken; we pitty the Sick, when we ſee their reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and painful ſtate, and hear their lamentable Shrieks and deadly Groans; we pitty the Poor and the Forlorn, the Fatherleſs, Motherleſs, Friendleſs, Harbourleſs, Helpleſs, when we ſee them with naked Feet, and half-naked Bodies, in the pinching Severity of Froſt and Snow, ſeeking their Bread in deſolate places; we pitty poor Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, that lye in Dungeons, are brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Irons, ſink in the deep Mire, or elſe are made faſt in the Stocks, ſed with black Bread and cold Water, lodg'd on a little Litter amongſt Toads, and Newts, and noiſom Vermin; we pitty poor baniſh'd men, driven out of their own ſweet Country, and from amongſt their dear Relations, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring amongſt wild Beaſts, or barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous men, more ſavage than Beaſts, enjoying no Liberty, except it be that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:98767:61"/> of wandring from one Cave or Den or Deſart to another; we pitty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Princes, whoſe Crowns are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from their Heads, and the Children of prodigal Gentlemen, Lords of Towns, who come to be reliev'd by the Towns whereof their Fathers were ſometimes Lords. Oh! but how much more reaſon have we to pitty and bewail vain Mankind, the miſerable Poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> wounded in Soul with a moſt deadly wound, all their Bones broken, ſick of the moſt painful Diſeaſe and loathſom Leproſie, poor and deſolate, naked and forlorn, Slaves and Priſoners in the Dungeon of the Body, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sathan their Jayler, buniſht from Paradiſe, eſtranged from God and his holy Angels, and wandring in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of this World in a thouſand Wants, Neceſſities, Dangers, Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties, and Perplexities, degraded from their excellent Honour and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and now feeding upon Husks or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:98767:62"/> to be Ment for Swine! When <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaw the lame man that could not walk at all, they pittied him and healed him. When we conſider poor Mankind walking in a <hi>vain ſhew,</hi> though we cannot heal them, let us pitty and pray for them, and bewail our own and their Degeneracy. Nay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Let us not only bewail the Vanity of Mankind, but be in a godly ſence weary of our vain Life. The higheſt pitch which moſt men aim at, is but this, to be deſirous to live, and content to dye: But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was of a higher form, he was only content to live, but deſirous to dye, deſirous to depart, and to be with Chriſt, becauſe it was far better, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. Poſſibly you will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to argue from the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19. 4. <hi>Lord, take away my life;</hi> nor from holy <hi>Job, chap.</hi> 7.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:98767:62"/> 15, 16. <hi>My ſoul chooſeth death rather than life; I loath it, I would not live always, for my days are vanity.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you will ſay, theſe holy men were either in a <hi>Paſſion</hi> not to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, or in a <hi>Rapture</hi> not to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated; but yet ſure, in good earneſt, and in ſober Temper, without either Paſſion or Extaſie, the conſideration of our poor imperfect ſtate, and vain life, ought to beget in every Pilgrim Soul a holy and comely wearineſs of this ſtate of alienation and elongation from its GOD; I dare not venture to call it the Grace of Diſcontentment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Grace and Art of <hi>Contentment</hi> has obtained ſo great a Name in the World, but methinks a degree of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs or Diſcontentment, may well enough ſtand with a predominant ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to, and ſatisfaction in the Will of God. One thing cannot be deſired, (eſpecially not with ſuch a deſire as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> imports) but the contrary to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:98767:63"/> it, muſt be in ſome degree rejected or undervalued: So that I ſuppoſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>'s deſire to depart com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends in it a kind of wearineſs of Commoration in the Body. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, who can reaſonably blame a man that is weary of a ſtate of Bondage, Baniſhment, Impriſonment, Poverty, and Vanity, and deſires a ſtate of Liberty, Enlargement, and Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Which brings me to the laſt thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Study, covet, love and long after things durable and ſubſtantial. As we ought with a holy kind of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs to lead <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a life void of Pleaſure in things here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, ſo ought our life to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a flight of our Souls to God alone. The whole Creation is ſubjected to Vanity, but the Creature ſhall be delivered from the Bondage of Corruption; therefore <hi>the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:98767:63"/> 
               <hi>groaneth and travaileth in pain, Rom.</hi> 8. 20, 21, 22. And ſhall not we much rather long to be delivered from our ſtate of Vanity? Can we ſeriouſly think of our Vanity, Miſery, and Indigency, and not cry out, Oh that we <hi>were as in times paſt,</hi> when we came out of the Hands of God at firſt! or, Oh that we were as we ſhall be in <hi>time to come,</hi> when we ſhall be put into the Hands of God again. It is lawful, it is reaſonable, it is ſafe, it is ſeemly, to look for and long after a ſtate of Purity and Perfection, a ſtate of compleat Health and Liberty, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union with our God and Center, to be <hi>abſent from the Body, and preſent with the Lord.</hi> It is moſt natural and comely, for every thing to tend to its own Perfection; and the moſt <hi>health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Conſtitution of a Soul, is to be <hi>ſick</hi> of Love. The deſcription of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ſanctified Souls is, that they love the appearing of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:98767:64"/> 4. 8. that they look for his appearing, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 13. that they look for, or long for the Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto Eternal life, <hi>Jude, ver.</hi> 21. that they look for, and haſten to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the day of God, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 12. And ſo we find they have done, <hi>Paul</hi> deſiring to <hi>depart and to be with Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> longing for the Salvation of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 174. his Soul breaking for very longing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 20. wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the <hi>Lord</hi> more than they that watch for the Morning, I ſay, more than they, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 6.</p>
            <p>To conclude, Lament not intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately the removal of any out of this ſtate of <hi>Vanity and Vexation of Spirit,</hi> into a ſtate of ſatisfaction and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Spirit. Rejoice not immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately in the faireſt and ſweeteſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of this preſent life, but live under a painful ſenſe of your own Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, breathing after a ſtate ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:98767:64"/> and durable, bliſsful and eternal: And God of his infinite Mercy grant, that we always endeavouring to perfect Holineſs in the fear of God, at our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval hence, may have an abundant Entrance adminiſtred unto us, into the Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt;</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>To whom, with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Praiſe, Honour, and Glory, for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. line 8. read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; p. 2. l. 4. r. <hi>male;</hi> p. 29. l. 19. r. <hi>in</hi> 3 p. 100. l. 7. r. <hi>requiſivit;</hi> p. 106. l. 8. 8. <hi>velleity.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98767:65"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books printed for Tho. Parkhurſt <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns <hi>in</hi> Cheapſide.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Books in Folio.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>RIchard Baxter's</hi> Catholick Theology, plain, pure, peaceable, for pacification of the Dogmatical Word-Warriours. In three Book.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Methodus Theologiae Chriſtianae:</hi> By Mr. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Baxter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sixty one Sermons, preached moſtly on publick Occaſions. By <hi>Adam Littleton</hi> D. D. Rector of <hi>Chelſey</hi> in <hi>Middleſex, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One Hundred ſelect Sermons upon ſeveral Texts, Fifty upon the Old Teſtament, and Fifty on the New.</item>
               <item>Choice and Practical Expoſitions on Four ſelect Pſalms. Theſe two by the Reverend and Learned <hi>Tho. Horton,</hi> D. D. late Miniſter of Great St. <hi>Hellens, London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A third Volume of Sermons preached by the late Reverend and Learned <hi>Tho. Manton,</hi> D. D. In two parts, the firſt containing Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Six Sermons on the Eleventh Chapter of the <hi>Hebrews:</hi> With a Treatiſe of the Life of Faith. Part the ſecond<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A Treatiſe of Self-denial; with ſeveral Sermons on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's Supper, and other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; with an alphabetical Table to the whole.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:98767:65"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
